<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prima the first things, in reference to the middle and last things: or, the doctrine of regeneration, the new birth, the very beginning of a godly life. Delivered by Isaac Ambrose, minister of the Gospel at Preston in Amounderness in Lancashire.</title>
            <title>Prima, media, &amp; ultima. Prima.</title>
            <author>Ambrose, Isaac, 1604-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826230</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826230</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30627</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30627)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1822:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prima the first things, in reference to the middle and last things: or, the doctrine of regeneration, the new birth, the very beginning of a godly life. Delivered by Isaac Ambrose, minister of the Gospel at Preston in Amounderness in Lancashire.</title>
                  <title>Prima, media, &amp; ultima. Prima.</title>
                  <author>Ambrose, Isaac, 1604-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.F. for I.A. and are to be sold by Nathanael Webb and William Grantham, at the Greyhound in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCL. [1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The new birth.</note>
                  <note>The first part of "Prima, media, &amp; ultima".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Regeneration (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30627:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRIMA, THE FIRST THINGS, In reference to <hi>The Middle</hi> and <hi>Laſt Things:</hi> Or, The Doctrine of REGENERATION, THE <hi>NEW BIRTH,</hi> The very beginning of a godly life. Delivered by ISAAC AMBROSE, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel at</hi> PRESTON in Amounderneſs <hi>in</hi> Lancaſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 5.17.</hi>
               </bibl> If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature: Old things are paſſed away, behold all things are become new.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J.F.</hi> for <hi>I.A.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Nathanael Webb</hi> and <hi>William Grantham,</hi> at the Greyhound in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <hi>MDCL.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30627:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30627:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful, The MAYOR, ALDERMEN, And other INHABITANTS IN The Town of <hi>Preſton</hi> in <hi>Amounderneſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle <hi>Peter knowing</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>that ſhortly he was to put off that his tabernacle of the fleſh,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.14, 15</note> as our Lord Jeſus Chriſt had ſhewed him;</hi> he therefore <hi>endeavored that Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, after his deceaſe, might have thoſe things he taught them always in remembrance:</hi> And thus it came to paſs, that to this day we have that portion of holy Writ which he then left in writing. If <hi>Peters</hi> practice be imitable in this kinde, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſame duty lies on
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si</hi> M. T. <hi>Ciceroni tanta fuit cura de ſua republica, ut ſcripſit in lib. de Amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi>—Mihi autem non minori curae eſt qualis reſp. poſt mortem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am futura ſit, quàm qualis hodie eſt: <hi>Multò magis incumbat mihi cura de anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſalute ut benè cedat illis poſtquam ego è vivis exiero, ae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ut jam ante obitum meum.</hi>
               </note> me. Revelation I have none, but many ſtitches and infirmities, which <hi>I</hi> take to be fore-runners of my departure hence. Some things, and amongst the reſt, theſe <hi>Firſt Things,
<pb facs="tcp:30627:3"/>I</hi> have <hi>taught</hi> you; what remains now, but that <hi>after my deceaſe you might have theſe things always in remembrance?</hi> To that purpoſe, the ſame <hi>I</hi> delivered once to your ears, <hi>I</hi> now preſent to your eyes; as you were then pleaſed to hear them, ſo <hi>I</hi> truſt you will now peruſe them: Onely one thing you may pleaſe to obſerve through this Treatiſe, That whereas in the Name of Chriſt <hi>I</hi> often Beſeech, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, Command the unregenerate to believe, to be reconciled to God, to pray, to fall on this or that duty, it is not as if they could do any thing of their own ſtrength or power; but becauſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in Exhorting, Entreating, Commanding, puts forth his own power, and his own ſtrength to enable them. While <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the Goaler to believe in the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that he might be ſaved, <hi>God</hi> enabled the Goalor to believe. Life and power is conveyed to the ſoul, in Gospel-Commands and Exhortations. While <hi>Ezekiel</hi> propheſied over dead bones, breath came into them, and they lived: ſo while the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the Lord do preach over ſinful impenitent hearers, who are like to the Prophets dry bones, the breath of Heaven, the Spirit of the Moſt High in the Miniſtery of the Gospel, enters into them, and ſo they are made new creatures, and ſee the Kingdom of
<pb facs="tcp:30627:3"/>
               <hi>God.</hi> I have no more to ſay, onely I beſeech <hi>God</hi> you may receive a Bleſsing by theſe poor labors upon your poor ſouls: it is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to be commanded in all Chriſtian Services,</hi> Iſaac Ambroſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30627:4"/>
            <head>To his worthily much eſteemed Friend, Mr. <hi>Iſaac Ambroſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have peruſed your hearty <hi>Travel</hi> in this happy Birth; and therein (I dare ſay) as your <hi>induſtry and skill,</hi> ſo your intereſt and birthright, your Labor either way. This <hi>ſubject</hi> could not be ſo well <hi>handled,</hi> if not <hi>felt;</hi> he muſt himſelf be <hi>ſubject,</hi> as well as <hi>Author,</hi> that doth it ſo well. No man can be here <hi>Eloquent,</hi> unleſs <hi>Experient; Propriety</hi> of <hi>Title,</hi> can onely here give <hi>Propriety</hi> of <hi>Language:</hi> How like the motion, the language of a Puppet in a Play is the beſt Pulpit-Pageant in this <hi>Theame</hi> of the unintereſſed man? My Prayer is that of the Apoſtle, That all of us Miniſters <hi>may be (herein) able to comfort others,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>by the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort wherewith we our ſelves are comforted of God:</hi> And what comfort like this, that makes us, with the woman,
<note place="margin">Iohn 16.21.</note> 
               <hi>forget all our ſorrows, for joy that the childe is born?</hi> What is it (otherwiſe) to be <hi>born</hi> to <hi>learn,</hi> if we <hi>learn</hi> not thus to be <hi>born?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdom</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is good with an Inheritance;</hi> how good is this <hi>wiſdom</hi> then, that by this <hi>New Birth</hi> not onely <hi>preſerves,</hi> but <hi>intitles</hi> to that <hi>Inheritance of the Saints in light?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.12.</note> Wherein, that this your <hi>birth</hi> of that <hi>Birth</hi> may be to many <hi>Generations fruitful,</hi> is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true Friend, <hi>CHARLES HERLE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:30627:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS of <hi>PRIMA,</hi> OR The Firſt Things.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe neceſſity of Regeneration,</hi> Page 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The generality and ſubject of Regeneration,</hi> Page 7</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The maner of Regeneration,</hi> Page 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The iſſue and effects of Regeneration,</hi> Page 42</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>An Appendix, containing a more particular method of Regeneration: Wherein</head>
               <item>Chap. 1. <hi>THe occaſion and method of this Treatiſe,</hi> Pag. 49.</item>
               <item>Chap. 2.
<list>
                     <item>Sect. 1. <hi>The firſt means to get into the New Birth,</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>Sect. 2, &amp;c. <hi>Sins againſt the firſt Commandment to the laſt,</hi> 51</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>The ſecond means to get into the New Birth,</hi> 59</item>
               <item>Chap. 4.
<list>
                     <item>Sect. 1. <hi>The third means to get into the New Birth,</hi> 60</item>
                     <item>Sect. 2, &amp;c. <hi>The firſt, ſecond and third reaſon for ſorrow,</hi> 61</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 5.
<list>
                     <item>Sect. 1. <hi>The means to be delivered out of the pangs of the New Birth,</hi> 63</item>
                     <item>Sect. 2. <hi>The Promiſes procuring a ſight of Chriſt,</hi> 64</item>
                     <item>Sect. 3. <hi>The Promiſes procuring a deſire after Chriſt,</hi> 65</item>
                     <item>Sect. 4. <hi>The Promiſes procuring a relying on Chriſt,</hi> 66</item>
                     <item>Sect. 5. <hi>The Promiſes procuring obedience to Chriſt,</hi> 67</item>
                     <item>Sect. 6. <hi>The Promiſes procuring comfort in Chriſt,</hi> 68</item>
                     <item>Sect. 7. <hi>The means to apply the ſaid Promiſes,</hi> 70</item>
                     <item>Sect. 8. <hi>The Concluſion,</hi> 71</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:30627:5"/>
            <head>To the Reverend AUTHOR, on his learned TREATISES, Intituled, <hi>Prima, Media &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima,</hi> THE Firſt, Middle and Laſt Things.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe <hi>Firſt,</hi> and <hi>Laſt,</hi> and <hi>Middle</hi> Things: What more?</l>
               <l>Thus the well-furniſh'd Scribe out of his ſtore</l>
               <l>Brings new and old. The <hi>Firſt</hi> Things lay the Ground,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Middle</hi> Build thereon; By th' <hi>Laſt</hi> All's crown'd.</l>
               <l>By the <hi>Firſt</hi> Things Chriſtians begin to live;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Middle</hi> Things a further progreſs give</l>
               <l>In Spiritual life; by th' <hi>Laſt</hi> they live for ever:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thoſe things that God hath joyn'd, let no man ſever.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Things wrought in me (Lord!) let me finde,</l>
               <l>And to the <hi>Middle</hi> ſo direct my minde,</l>
               <l>That when the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Middle</hi> Things are paſt,</l>
               <l>I may enjoy my hopes; The Beſt at <hi>Laſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T.W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30627:5"/>
            <head>The new Birth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOH. 3.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E read in the former Chapter, John 2.23.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.23. <hi>Nicodemus ex his erat qui crediderant in nomine ejus, videntes ſigna &amp; prodigia quae faciobat. Aug. Tract. in Ioan.</hi> Ioh. 7.48.</note> 
               <hi>When Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was at Jeruſalem, at the feaſt of the Paſsover, many believed in his name when they ſaw the miracles which he did:</hi> Amongſt thoſe many, here is one of them (ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi>) what one? of all men the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely is a Jew, of all Jews a Ruler, of all Rulers a Phariſee; <hi>Have any of the Rulers, or the Phariſees believed on him?</hi> But howſoever it ſeem thus unlikely unto us, the Spirit of God <hi>blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where it liſteth;</hi> here is amongſt <hi>many believers</hi> one <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus,</hi> and he is <hi>a man of the Phariſees, a Ruler of the Jews;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ. </seg>1</label> a Jew, a Ruler, a Phariſee,
<note place="margin">Luk. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>God is able even of theſe ſtones to raiſe up children unto Abraham;</hi> yea, we ſee here (be they never ſo ſtony) our Saviour melts one of them with a miracle, and by a <hi>new birth</hi> he will make him a ſon of <hi>Abraham</hi> indeed. A miracle brings him to Chriſt, and Chriſt brings him to a <hi>new birth:</hi> The firſt <hi>Nicodemus</hi> confeſſeth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Rabbi</hi> (faith he to our Savior) <hi>we know that thou art a Teacher come from God, for no man can do theſe miracles that thou doſt, except God be with him.</hi> The ſecond our Savior affirmeth, as if he had anſwered, to ſay, <hi>I am ſent from God,</hi> and not to be <hi>born again,</hi> will never help thee to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; thy confeſſion is right, that <hi>I am ſent from God,</hi> but thy converſation is wrong, that art not <hi>born again:</hi> thou comeſt to me with confeſſion of thy faith, but here is a further Catechiſm, another leſſon; and therefore (as thou calleſt me <hi>Rabbi</hi>) if thou wilt be a Scholar in my School, thou muſt learn theſe principles, theſe rudiments, theſe <hi>firſt things,</hi> this text, this A, B, C, of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30627:6"/>an Religion, <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannst ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proſecution of which words (all tending to this one point of the <hi>new birth</hi>) we ſhall follow the order ſet down by the Holy Ghoſt, where is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The neceſſity of it, no going to heaven without it, <hi>Except.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The generality of it, every man is bound to it, <hi>a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The maner of it, how a man is wrought in it, he muſt <hi>be born again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The iſſue of it, what effects are annext to it, <hi>the Kingdom of God, and ſight of that Kingdom; a man that is born again ſhall ſee the Kingdom of God;</hi> and, <hi>Except a man be born again, he ſhall not ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Theſe be the branches, and of every of them (by Gods aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) we ſhall gather ſome fruit for the food of your ſouls. The firſt branch is the firſt word, <hi>Except.</hi>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Except]</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Except</hi> is without exception, for unleſs we are new born, there is no going to Heaven: before we live here we are born, and before we live there we are new born; as no man comes into this world, but by the firſt birth, ſo impoſſible it is that any ſhould go to Heaven in another world, but by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond birth: And this gives us the neceſſity of Regeneration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except a man be new born,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>he can never be ſaved.</hi> It is our Saviors ſpeech, and he confirms it with a double aſſeveration, <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee.</hi> Twice <hi>verily,</hi> which we finde not any where but in S. <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Rupert. in loc.</note> and no where in the Goſpel ſo oft as on this argument: how then ſhould we disbelieve this truth, where we have ſuch a witneſs as Chriſt, ſuch a teſtimony as his <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, God the Father thus counſels, not onely <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> but all the Jews of the old Church,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.31.</note> ſaying, <hi>Make you a new heart, and a new ſpirit, for why will you dye, O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> Ezek. 18.31. Notwithſtanding all their priviledges (for they <hi>are Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.4.</note> 
                  <hi>to whom pertains the adoption, and the glory, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30627:6"/>promiſes,</hi> Rom. 9.4.) Yet here is <hi>one thing neceſſary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vuum neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</note> that muſt crown all the reſt; they muſt have <hi>a new heart, and a new ſpirit,</hi> that is to ſay, they muſt be <hi>new born,</hi> or there is no way but death; from which death ſee how the Lord pulls them with his cords of love, alluring, wooing, queſtioning, <hi>Why will ye dye, O houſe of Iſrael?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet again, not onely the Son and the Father,
<note place="margin">Revel. 2.17.</note> but the Holy Ghoſt too will avouch this truth; <hi>He that hath an ear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mos erat an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquis niveis atriſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> lapillis his damnare reos, illis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvere paena. Metamorphoſ. l.</hi> 15.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hunc macrine diem numera meliore lapillo. Perſ. Sat: ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aretius in loc.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.17.</p>
                  </note> And what's that? <hi>To him that overcometh — will I give a white ſtone, and in the ſtone a new name written: yea, I will write upon him New Jeruſalem, and I will write upon him my new name,</hi> Revel. 2.17. and 3.12. The meaning is, he that is <hi>new born,</hi> and ſo overcomes ſin Gods Spirit will give him his grace, <hi>the white ſtone,</hi> and his Kingdom, <hi>the new Jeruſalem, and a new name,</hi> the name of filia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (ſaith a Modern) whereby truly he is called the <hi>new born</hi> Son of God. See here how <hi>old things being done away, all things are become new; by a new birth</hi> man hath got a <hi>new name, a new inheritance:</hi> and therefore as the Spirit, ſo the <hi>new birth</hi> is called a <hi>fire,</hi> that purgeth away droſs, and makes ſouls bright and new, ſo that we muſt paſs thorow this <hi>fire,</hi> or no paſſage into <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is this Doctrine without reaſon or ground.</p>
               <p>For, <hi>Except</hi> by the ſecond birth, man is firſt unholy,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> and therefore moſt unfit to enter into Heaven: <hi>Without holineſs no man ſhall ſee God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. And what is man before he is <hi>new born?</hi> if we look upon his ſoul, we may ſee it deformed with ſin, defiled with luſt, outraged with paſſions, overcarried with affections, pining with envy, burthened with gluttony, boyling with revenge, tranſported with rage, and thus is that Image of God transformed to the ugly ſhape of the Devil: Or ſhould we take a more particular view, every faculty of the ſoul is full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity; the underſtanding underſtands nothing of <hi>the things of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. the will wills nothing <hi>that is good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14. Rom. 6.20. Gal. 5.17.</note> Rom. 6.20. the affections affect nothing of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.17. In a word, the underſtanding is darkned, the will enthralled, the affections diſordered, the memory defiled, the conſcience benummed, all the inner man is full of ſin, and there is no part that is good, <hi>no not one.</hi> But what ſay we of the body? ſure that is nothing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30627:7"/>it is a rotten carrion, altogether unprofitable, and good for nothing; ſhould we view it in every part and member of it? the head contrives miſchief, the eyes behold vanity, the ears let in ſin, the tongue ſends out oaths: Come we lower, the heart lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth luſts, the hands commit murther, the feet run to evil, all the ſenſes are but ſo many matches to give fire to luſts, deceits, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, and what not? How needful now is a <hi>new birth</hi> to a man in this caſe? Can he enter into heaven, that ſavours all of earth? Will thoſe precious gates of gold and pearls open to a ſinner? No, he muſt firſt be new moulded, and ſanctified, or he is <hi>except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Except a man be new born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Except</hi>] This, and man, is Gods enemy; no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oppoſition than betwixt God and a ſinner: Conſider we him in his eſſence, or in his attributes? in his eſſence he is called <hi>Jehovah,</hi> both in reſpect of his being, and of his promiſes; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his being, and ſo God is contrary to ſin; for ſin is <hi>ataxy,</hi> diſorder, confuſion, a not-being; and God is order, perfection, holineſs, an abſolute and a ſimple being: in reſpect likewiſe of his promiſes, wherein there is a main oppoſition to ſin; for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he promiſeth a reward to the regenerate, and ſo the name <hi>Jehovah</hi> is a golden pledge unto us,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.6.</note> that if we repent, he will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us; yet withal he promiſeth <hi>ſtorms</hi> and <hi>tempeſt, fire</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> to the unregenerate: and thus his name and nature is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether oppoſite to ſin and ſinners. But view we thoſe attributes of God, I mean his Juſtice, truth, patience, holineſs, anger, power: his Juſtice, in puniſhing the impenitent according to his deſerts, his truth effecting thoſe plagues which he hath ſpoken in his time, his patience forbearing ſins deſtruction, till they are grown full ripe, his holineſs abhorring all impurities, <hi>He cannot behold iniquity,</hi> his anger ſtirring up revenge againſt all offered injuries, his power muſtring up his forces, yea all his creatures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his enemies; and what can we ſay, but if all theſe attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes are at enmity with ſinful man, woe worth to man becauſe of offences! better he had never been born, then not to be <hi>new born;</hi> alas! what ſhall become of him? Can he that is Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſee God in his glory? no, there is no way but one, <hi>Except he repent, Except] he be born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12. 1 Cor. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Except</hi>] by a new birth, man is <hi>without Chriſt;</hi> for <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature:</hi> And if he be not in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30627:7"/>Chriſt, what hopes of that man? It is onely Chriſt that opens Heaven, it is onely Chriſt that is the <hi>Way</hi> to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; beſides him there is no <hi>Way,</hi> no <hi>Truth,</hi> no <hi>Life;</hi> and if we be in him, <hi>as the branch in the vine,</hi> it is of neceſſity that we bring forth good fruit: Upon theſe terms his death is effectual, if we become new <hi>creatures;</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, all his Merits (his blood that was ſhed, his body that was crucified, his ſoul that was agonized) they are nothing unto us, we nothing bettered by them: he dyed for all, but his death is not applyed, his Kingdom is not opened, ſave onely unto them that have learned and practiſed this rule of <hi>Exception: Except] a man be born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Except</hi> before <hi>Excepted,</hi> a man is a very limb of Satan, a childe of darkneſs, and one of the Family of Hell. Conſider this, ye that are out of the ſtate of Grace, in what miſerable thraldom is your ſouls? Should any call you ſervants, or ſlaves of Satan, you would take it highly in diſdain; but take it as you pleaſe, if you are not regenerate, you are in no better caſe. <hi>Paul</hi> appeals to your own knowledge,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.16, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Know you not that to whomſoever you give your ſelves as ſervants to obey, his ſervants ye are to whom ye obey?</hi> Rom. 6.16, 23. If then ye obey the Devils ſuggeſtions (which you do being unborn) what are you but the Devils ſervants? And if he be your Maſter, what is you wages? You may ſee it in the laſt verſe, <hi>The wages of ſin is death;</hi> death of the body, and death of the ſoul, death here, and death hereafter in Hell fire. Alas, that Satan ſhould have this power on man! that he who is the enemy, and means nothing to a ſinner but death and damnation, ſhould be his Lord, and Tyrannize it over him at his own will and pleaſure! Would any man be hired to ſerve Lyons and Tygers?
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> And is not the Devil <hi>a roaring Lyon, walking about, and ſeeking whom he may devour?</hi> To ſerve him that would devour his ſervant, is a moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable bondage; and what pay can one expect from De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, but <hi>roaring</hi> and <hi>devouring,</hi> and tearing ſouls? In this plight are <hi>the ſervants of Corruption,</hi> ſlaves of Satan, ſo I rightly call them; for, <hi>Of whomſoever a man is overcome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>even unto the ſame is he in bondage,</hi> 2 Peter 2.19. To winde
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30627:8"/>up this point; <hi>Lord, who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle? who ſhall reſt in thy Holy Mountain?</hi> If we believe <hi>David, Not he that ſlandereth with his tongue, or doth evil to his Neighbor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 15.1, 3, 5.</note>—<hi>Or giveth his money upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, or taketh a reward againſt the innocent:</hi> No, ſuch are ſervants of Satan, and here is matter of <hi>Exception</hi> againſt them; <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>The ſum of all: <hi>Without Regeneration no Kingdom;</hi> for, whether we conſider man in regard <hi>of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or of God, or of Chriſt, or of Satan,</hi> he is <hi>(Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be new born) unholy, Gods enemy, out of Chriſt, in Satan.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And if the <hi>New Birth</hi> be thus neceſſary; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> how ſhould we
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Thus is the language of God; <hi>I ſaid, Behold me, to a nation that was not called by my Name,</hi> Iſa. 65.1.</note> labor to <hi>be born again?</hi> I mean not as <hi>Nicodemus, to enter into our mothers womb again, and be born;</hi> It is not the ſeed of man in the womb of our Mother, but the ſeed of Grace in the womb of the Church, that makes us bleſſed: and if we are thus born by Grace, then are we ſanctified, made Sons of God, Heirs with Chriſt, over whom Satan can have no power at all. Now then, as you tender your ſouls, and deſire Heaven at your ends,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Thus whileſt the Miniſter ſpeaks its Chriſt comes with power in the word, <hi>Eze.</hi> 18.31.</note> endeavor to attain this <hi>one thing neceſſary:</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pray, becauſe <hi>God</hi> bids you pray, it may be he will come in when you pray. When <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was in the gall of bitterneſs, <hi>Peter</hi> bid him pray <hi>Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 8 22.</note> Lift up your hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, that you may be <hi>waſhed, juſtified; ſanctified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> and that by the Spirit of God you may walk in new ways, talk with new tongues, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new creatures, created unto good works. Thus would you
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Not that we can wait by a power of our own, but he that ſaith, <hi>Therefore will the Lord wait, that be may be gracious to you,</hi> Iſa. 30.18. He draws, and gives a power to wait on him, and he comes in when he hath waited the fitteſt time.</note> wait on God in his way, I truſt the Lord in mercy would remember you, and his Spirit would <hi>blow</hi> upon you. and then you would finde and feel ſuch a change within you, as that you would bleſs God for ever, that you were thus <hi>born again:</hi> Otherwiſe, how woful are you, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this bar in heavens door, to keep out the unregenerate. <hi>Except] Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far of the <hi>Exception;</hi> we now come to the <hi>Perſon,</hi> that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30627:8"/>is a <hi>Niſi prius</hi> in the front, <hi>Except:</hi> This is the party that muſt proſecute the cauſe, <hi>a man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A man]</head>
               <p>ANd this <hi>man</hi>] is every man, and every part of man: It implyes all men, for all are bound to it, and all man; for all the parts of his body, and all the powers of his ſoul are to be renewed, or he cannot be ſaved: The word then is general, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we reſpect <hi>genera ſingulorum,</hi> the kindes, all men; or <hi>ſingula generum,</hi> the <hi>Individuums,</hi> all man, or all the parts of man, body and ſoul.</p>
               <p>We will firſt begin with the kindes: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>All men (or all mankinde) muſt be regenerated before they be ſaved;</hi> not one of all the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> that ſhall ever go to heaven, <hi>except he be born again:</hi> may your contemplations (guided by Gods word) go into that Paradiſe above, there walk the ſtreets, behold the towers, view the ſubjects, <hi>from the one end of heaven to another,</hi> and whom finde you there? Not one that lives and dyes in ſin; there is not in it, nor ſhall <hi>enter into it any thing that defileth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 21.27.</note> 
                  <hi>neither what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever worketh abomination, or maketh a lye,</hi> Revel. 21.27. yet if ſuch repent them of their ſins, <hi>the gates ſhall not be ſhut againſt them,</hi> all the Saints that now <hi>walk in the light of it,</hi> were ſinners; but firſt they were purged by the Lamb, and ſanctified by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; firſt they were regenerated, and ſo they were ſaved.</p>
               <p>You may object, If all men that go to heaven muſt be <hi>new born,</hi> what ſhall become of infants, that dye ere they be born? <hi>Can a man enter the ſecond time into his mothers womb, and be born?</hi> (ſaid <hi>Nicodemus</hi>) But can a man enter into the ſecond birth in his mothers womb (ſay you) and be <hi>born again,</hi> before he is once born?</p>
               <p>I anſwer <hi>[to be born again]</hi> ſuppoſeth to be once born in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; therefore according to the letter, our Savior ſpeaketh of <hi>a man</hi> already born into the world, that he muſt <hi>be born again:</hi> But if we ſeek out the ſenſe <hi>[to be born again]</hi> (as our Savior interprets) is <hi>to be born of water and of the Spirit;</hi> and ſo may Infants not born into the world <hi>be born again.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 1.5.</note> Thus we read of <hi>Jeremy, The word of the Lord came unto him, ſaying, Before I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30627:9"/>formed thee in the belly, I knew thee, and before thou cameſt forth out of the womb, I ſanctified thee,</hi> Jer. 1.5. And thus we read of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, the Angel of the Lord ſaying of him, that <hi>He ſhould be filled with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.15.</note> 
                  <hi>even from his mothers womb,</hi> Luk. 1.15. By theſe examples we ſee what the Lord can do; yea, what he doth indeed, although we know not how, nor can it be obſerved by us.</p>
               <p>You may yet object, <hi>[to be born again]</hi> is (ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or) <hi>[to be born of water and of the Spirit:]</hi> now <hi>water</hi> is the outward Baptiſm, and <hi>the Spirit</hi> is the inward grace (thus
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quindecem patres propoſuit Bellarminus. Tomo ſecundo lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de effectu Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Hook. Eccleſ. Polit. l.</hi> 5. <hi>ſect.</hi> 59.</note> all Ancients have conſtrued this text, ſaith <hi>Hooker</hi>) but children not born (howſoever they are ſanctified by the Spirit) they cannot be baptized with water, and therefore they <hi>cannot ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer: In caſes of extremity, or impoſſibility, if actual Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm be wanting, vocal is enough, and thus far ſome of our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries grant us;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 3. <hi>part. quaeſt.</hi> 68. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Though it be wanting indeed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas) yet Baptiſm in deſire is ſufficient to ſalvation:</hi> And to this end he cites <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Sanctification may be without Baptiſm, and Baptiſm without Sanctification; if Sanctification be, though Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm be not, it avails to ſalvation; but if Baptiſm be, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication be not, it avails nothing at all.</hi> Our concluſion is this, <hi>All men</hi> (or all mankinde) <hi>yong men and maidens, old men and children,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 148.12.</note> all muſt be regenerated, or they can never <hi>ſee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> as all <hi>men,</hi> ſo all <hi>man</hi>] all the members of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, all the faculties of his ſoul. <hi>Sanctification (if ſaving) muſt be perfect and entire, though not in reſpect of degrees, yet in reſpect of parts;</hi> every part and power of body and ſoul muſt have its part of ſanctification, though no part his full perfection, before the diſſolution of our earthly tabernacles: Hence (ſay Divines) there is a regeneration or ſanctification (it is all one) <hi>inchoata</hi> and <hi>conſummata; inchoata,</hi> begun in this life, <hi>conſummata,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in that other: and of this ſaith our Savior, Matth. 19.28. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 19.28.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye which have followed me in the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, when the Son of man ſhall ſit in the throne of his glory, ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Iſrael:</hi> we ſpeak not of this <hi>Regeneration,</hi> but of that which brings to this, for we muſt be regenerated here, or have no part there with God in his glory.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30627:9"/>
               <p>And ſhould we conſider <hi>man</hi> in his parts, every part muſt bear a part in this birth; his <hi>body</hi> muſt be regenerated, his <hi>ſoul</hi> muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed: we will begin with the <hi>body; As you have yielded your members ſervants to uncleanneſs, and to iniquity unto iniquity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.19.</note> 
                  <hi>even ſo now yield your members ſervants to righteouſneſs, unto holineſs,</hi> Rom. 6.19. As every member of the <hi>old man</hi> is full of ſin, ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very member of the <hi>new born man</hi> is to be renewed by grace: To inſtance in ſome of them; <hi>The heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 15.19.</note> that in the <hi>old man</hi> is full of <hi>evil thoughts, murthers, adulteries, fornications, thefts, falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, blaſphemies;</hi> in the <hi>new man</hi> it is the member that muſt firſt be renewed, here grace firſt ſeats it ſelf, and after is diſperſed over all; as in natural generation the heart is firſt framed, ſo in ſpiritual regeneration the heart is firſt reformed. Some call it the firſt mover of all mens actions, for as the firſt mover carrieth all the ſphaeres of heaven with it, ſo doth the heart carry all the members of the body with it: and therefore it is, that the <hi>new man</hi> begins firſt with his heart; for if that fountain be right, all the ſtreams of his deſires, purpoſes, affections, ſpeeches, actions, converſations, run ſweet, and clear, and pleaſant. Again, <hi>the eye</hi> that in the <hi>old man</hi> is the Broaker, that goes between the heart and the object, to make up the ſinful bargain,
<note place="margin">Matt. 6.23. 2 Pet. 1.14. Iob. 31.1.</note> that which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior calls <hi>an evil eye,</hi> S. <hi>Peter, an adulterous eye;</hi> in the <hi>new man</hi> it muſt be exerciſed on other objects, <hi>I made a covenant with mine eye</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job) why then ſhould I think upon a maid? I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) from whence cometh mine help.</hi> Again, <hi>the ear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 121.1. Pſal. 58.5.</note> that in the <hi>old man</hi> is <hi>ſtopped againſt the voyce of the Charmer, charm he never ſo wiſely;</hi> or if it be open, like Deaths Porter, it lets in ſin and Satan at every occaſion; in <hi>the new man</hi> it muſt be the gate of life, or the door of faith; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is not a member that the devil more envieth than the <hi>ear,</hi> as we ſee in the man poſſeſſed with a deaf Devil, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.25.
<note place="margin">Mar 9.25.</note> who poſſeſſed that ſence, as the moſt excellent, to hinder him from hearing. Again, <hi>the tongue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.6.</note> that in the <hi>old man</hi> is <hi>a world of iniquity, that defileth the whole body, that ſetteth on fire the courſe of nature, and is ſet on fire on hell;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note> in the <hi>new man</hi> it muſt be the trumpet of divine praiſe, or (as <hi>David</hi> calls it) <hi>the pen of a ready writer,</hi> uttering onely thoſe things which the heart enditeth in ſincerity and truth. To ſum up all in one, <hi>the heart</hi> is it, where grace begins firſt, and is felt laſt; and therefore ſaith God, <hi>Son,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30627:10"/>give me thy heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 23.26. Pſal. 51.10.</note> Prov. 23.26. and therefore prays <hi>David, Create in me a new heart,</hi> Pſal. 51.10. and therefore wills <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence, for out of it are the iſſues of life,</hi> Prov. 4.23. Would any man that is regenerate encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſin in his heart, it were impoſſible to break out into action; would the heart of any man that is <hi>born again,</hi> but meet ſin with this Dilemma, If I commit this ſin, I muſt either repent, or not repent for it; if I do repent, it will coſt me more heart-break, and ſpiritual ſmart, then the ſenſual pleaſure can be worth; If I never repent, it will be the death and damnation of my ſoul: ſure this thought conceived, and rightly followed in the heart of the regenerate, would be enough to cruſh ſin at the firſt riſing of it; and ſo it is, for if he be regenerate, he doth not ſin, <hi>whoſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.9. <hi>Conſuetudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, delectabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, ſervili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; illucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.23. Rom. 12.1.</note> 1 Joh. 3.9. He is moulded anew, and all the members of his body are conformed to the ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and rule of grace, yea <hi>his body is preſerved blameleſs, holy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God;</hi> it is a <hi>member of Chriſt, the temple of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Happy man that is bleſt with this body! Sure <hi>a man</hi> thus <hi>born again, he ſhall ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, as the <hi>body,</hi> ſo the <hi>ſoul</hi> of this <hi>man</hi> is to be renewed by grace;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.15, 19. 1 Cor. 6.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore glorifie God in your body and in your ſpirit,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.) the body and the ſpirit muſt both glorifie God; and as all the parts of the body, ſo all the powers of the ſoul.</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>the underſtanding,</hi> that in the <hi>old man</hi> is <hi>blinde and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> about heavenly things, or howſoever it may know many things,
<note place="margin">Revel. 3.18.</note> yet never can attain to ſaving knowledge; in the <hi>new man</hi> it muſt be anointed with the <hi>eye-ſalve</hi> of the Spirit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with the knowledge of Divine truths, eſpecially with thoſe ſacred and ſaving myſteries which concern <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi> Again, <hi>the will</hi> that in the <hi>old man</hi> affects nothing but vile and vain things, is froward and perverſe in the ways of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> in the <hi>new man</hi> it muſt prove and approve what is <hi>the good, and acceptable, and perfect will of God;</hi> yea, it muſt attend and be ſubordinate to the grace of God,
<note place="margin">Phil. 5.13.</note> ſith God indeed, and God onely <hi>works in us both the will and the deed,</hi> Phil. 2.13. Again, <hi>the memory</hi> that in the old man is ſlippery in the things of God, or if naturally good, yet not ſpiritually uſeful, in the <hi>new man</hi> it muſt be ſanctified to good performances; and although it cannot
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30627:10"/>encreaſe to a greater natural perfection (for grace doth not this) yet the perfections it hath muſt be ſtraight, and right, and guided to God-ward, <hi>Remember the Lord thy God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 8.18. Again,
<note place="margin">Deut. 8.18.</note> 
                  <hi>the conſcience</hi> that in the <hi>old man</hi> ſleeps and ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or if it be awake, tears and roars, as if a legion of Devils now poſſeſſed it; in the <hi>new man</hi> it muſt be calm and quiet, and yet not ſleep or ſlumber, but rather in a friendly loving maner check and control whereſoever ſin is, yea never be quiet, till with kinde and yet earneſt expoſtulations, it draw the ſinner before God to confeſs his fault, and to ſeek pardon for it. Again, <hi>the affections</hi> that in the <hi>old man</hi> are ſenſual, inordinate, bewitched, and ſet on wrong objects; in the <hi>new man</hi> they muſt be turned another way. <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> (you know) was given to unclean luſts, but the Lord diverted this ſinful paſſion, and ſo ſhe became penitent, and thirſted after grace: To ſum up all, all muſt be renewed, <hi>the undeſtanding, will, memory, conſcience, affections.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>But to feel more of their ſweetneſs, I will pound theſe ſpices, and dwell a while on them. Now then for your better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the regenerate man, and that you may know his difference from the man unregenerate, obſerve (I pray) theſe paſſages:</q>
               <p>Firſt, I ſay,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.10.</note> in the <hi>new man</hi> the underſtanding muſt be renewed; ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>The new man is renewed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Col. 3.10. and this knowledge implyes two habits,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.9. <hi>Sapientiam &amp; Prudentiam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Prudence, Col.</hi> 1.9. Firſt, <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and that is ſpeculative: Secondly, <hi>Prudence,</hi> and that is practical: By the one the childe of God having the eyes of his minde opened and illightned, doth ſee the myſteries of ſalvation, the ſecrets of the Kingdom, the whole Councel, and the wonders of the Law of God; by the other he is enabled with a judicious ſincerity, to deliberate and determine in caſes of conſcience, in the practice of piety, and the experimental paſſages of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man:
<note place="margin">Sapientiam.</note> If we conſider the firſt <hi>(Wiſdom)</hi> how is it poſſible that a man unregenerate ſhould know the myſteries of ſalvation? It may be he may go as far as the power of natural diſcourſe, and light of Reaſon can bear ſway, he may be furniſhed with ſtore of rare and excellent learning, and yet for all this want the true knowledge of <hi>ſpiritual wiſdom:</hi> Why ſo? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30627:11"/>all his knowledge, like the light of the Moon, is diſcharged upon others, but never returns and reflects upon his own ſoul; he ſhould know, but knows not the darkneſs of his own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the diſorder of his own affections, the ſlumber of his own conſcience, the deadneſs of his own heart; but the <hi>man</hi> regenerate (know he never ſo little) he hath the <hi>ſaving-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dge,</hi> and in this he exceeds the greateſt Rabbies, the profoundeſt Clerks; he onely knows God with a ſtedfaſt apprehenſion, he onely knows himſelf a moſt mean, baſe and contemptible thing; his <hi>new birth</hi> hath learned him how wicked a creature he natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is, and therefore in that reſpect is he odious to himſelf, and loathſom in his own eyes: Or if we conſider the ſecond <hi>(Prudence)</hi> How is it poſſible that a man unregenerate,
<note place="margin">Prudentiam.</note> ſhould experimentally know the practice of piety in a Chriſtian courſe? Should we inſtance in this myſtery of <hi>Regeneration;</hi> Here is one <hi>Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews, and a teacher of Iſrael;</hi> yet, as learned as he was, if he confer with Chriſt about the ſalvation of his ſoul, he is ſtrangely childiſh, and a meer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant; tell him of the <hi>new birth,</hi> and he thinks it as impoſſible, as for <hi>an old man to return into his mothers womb, and be born again:</hi> The natural man cannot diſcern the operations of grace, he knows not that dark and fearful paſſage, which leads from the ſtate of nature (through ſtrange terrors and torments of ſoul) into the rich and glorious happineſs of the kingdom of Chriſt; whereas on the contrary, the regenerate man (that hath had the experience of the power of godlineſs upon his own ſoul) he can ſee and judge of the light of grace, he can taſte and relliſh of the fruits of the Spirit; and hence it is, that many a ſilly one (man and woman) whom the worldly-wiſe paſs by with ſcorn and contempt, are often in ſpiritual affairs more wiſe and learned then the learnedſt Doctors.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Rectitudinem Promptitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> the Will muſt be renewed; and this will of the regenerate contains two things, Rightneſs and Readineſs: It is firſt rectified, when it is conformed to the will of God. Secondly, it is ſo inflamed with the love of goodneſs, that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly he purſues it with alacrity of ſpirit. If we conſider the firſt (the Rectitude of the will) we ſee by experience the will of the unregenerate is all out of courſe,
<note place="margin">Rectitudinem.</note> he wills nothing but that which is evil: How ſhould he, conſidering his want of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30627:11"/>Gods image, his blindeneſs of heart, his proneneſs to evil, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the vehemency of his affections, which draw the will after them, and trouble the judgement? But in the man that is regenerate, the will being moved, it afterwards moves it ſelf, Gods grace that concurs with it, quickens it, and revives it; ſo that now his will is nothing but Gods will: if it may appear that God bids him, or forbids him to do this, or that he chooſeth above all to follow his commands, whatſoever becomes of him; why, this is the very heart and marrow of regeneration; you may be ſure, the man that chooſeth above all to pleaſe God,
<note place="margin">Promptitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> is the onely man of God, and ſhall be rewarded by God. Or if we conſider the ſecond (the Readineſs of the will to God) alas, the will of the unregenerate hath no pleaſure in goodneſs, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands not the ſweetneſs of it,
<note place="margin">Iob 21.14.</note> and therefore nothing is more <hi>irkſom</hi> to him then the ways of godlineſs: whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the will of the regenerate is willing, and this willingneſs indeed is the perfection of his will; yea (if we can ſay more) it is the higheſt degree of his perfection in this life, to be willing to do good.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the <hi>memory</hi> muſt be renewed; and this <hi>memory</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects occaſionally on a double object, on God,
<note place="margin">Deum &amp; Dei verbum.</note> and the things of God: Firſt, on God, by remembrance of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence every where: Secondly, on the things of God, by calling them to minde at uſeful times. If we conſider the firſt object, God, the unregenerate hath no minde on God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deum.</hi> Pſal. 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>God is net in all his thoughts,</hi> like the hood-winkt fool, that ſeeing no body, thinks no body ſees him; ſo hath he ſaid in his heart,
<note place="margin">Job 22.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>How doth God know? can he judge thorow the dark cloud? Thick clouds are a covering to him that ſeeth not, and he walketh in the circuit of heaven.</hi> But contrariwiſe, the regenerare man,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ 12.1.</note> he <hi>remembers his Creator in the days of his youth.</hi> And though God, as being a Spirit, is (in ſome ſort) abſent from his ſenſes, yet by vertue of his ſanctified memory (that makes things abſent as preſent) his eye is on God, and he conſiders God as an eye-witneſs of all his thoughts, and words, and doings, and dealings; he knows nothing can be hid from that all-ſeeing eye, though ſin tempt him with the faireſt opportunities of night and darkneſs, yet ſtill he remembers, if his eye ſees nothing, all thoſe eyes of heaven (of God and of his Angels) are ever about him: and therefore he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30627:12"/>anſwers the Tempter, How dare I ſin to his face, that looks on me what I am doing? if I dare not do this folly before men, how dare I do it before thoſe heaven-ſpectators, God and his Angels? Or if we conſider the ſecond object <hi>(the Word of God)</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate never burthens his memory with ſuch bleſſed thoughts;
<note place="margin">Dei verbum.</note> if ſometimes he falls upon it, it is either by conſtraint, or by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, never with any ſetled reſolution to dwell on it, or to follow it:
<note place="margin">Luke 2.51. Pſal. 119.11.</note> but the ſoul that is regenerate, with <hi>Mary, keeps all theſe things in his heart;</hi> or with <hi>David,</hi> gives it out, <hi>Thy word have I hid in my heart,</hi> Pſal. 119.11. Whatſoever leſſons he learns, like ſo many jewels in a casket, he lays them up ſafe, and then as need ſerveth, he remembers his ſtore, and makes all the good uſe of them he may: I will not deny, but any man (good or evil) may retain good things according to that ſtrength of retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which nature affords him, but the regenerate (whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory onely is ſanctified) whatſoever he retains, he hath it op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely at hand; in tentation or affliction he remembers and applyes, and ſo remembring to apply, and applying that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, he is thereby inabled to reſiſt evil, or to follow thoſe good things which the Lord hath commanded.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the conſcience muſt be renewed, and that two ways;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad bonum,</hi> or <hi>a malo.</hi>
                  </note> either by drawing the ſoul to good, or from evil: firſt, to good, by inclining and incouraging; and ſecondly, from evil, by reſtraining and bridling. If we conſider its firſt office (in that it draws and leads the ſoul <hi>to good</hi>) I confeſs the unregenerate is not of that conſcience,
<note place="margin">Ad bonum.</note> for the moſt part his conſcience lies dead in his boſom, or if it ſtir ſometimes, he labors all he can to ſmother it in his waking: to ſuch an one ſhould men and Angels preach, yet ſo far is he bewitched with ſin, that he hath no minde of goodneſs, or if ever he do any good act (which is a rare thing with him) it is not out of conſcience to do good, but for ſome ſiniſter end or reſpect. It is otherwiſe with the regenerate, his conſcience incites him to good, and he doth good out of conſcience; he ſtands not upon terms of pleaſure or profit, but his conſcience being guided by the rule and ſquare of Gods holy truth, he ſubmits to it meerly out of his obedience to God: hence it is, that come what will come, weal or wo, his eye is fixt on God, and if man oppoſe where God commands, he is quickly reſolved out of that in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 51.12.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 51.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I, even I am he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30627:12"/>you; who art thou, that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a man that ſhall dye, and of the ſon of man that ſhall be made as graſs? and forgetteſt the Lord thy maker, that hath ſtretched forth the heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth?</hi> Or if we conſider the ſecond office of conſcience (in drawing the ſoul <hi>from evil</hi>) the unregenerate either hears not,
<note place="margin">A malo.</note> or heeds not his reclaiming conſcience: if it ſpeak, he firſt goes about to lull it aſleep again, or if it cry out, and will not peace, then (in ſpight of goodneſs) he runs out of one ſin into another, and uſually from preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to deſpair. On the other ſide, the regenerate hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that draws him from, and keeps him out of evil: 'tis known eſpecially by theſe two properties, <hi>Remorſe</hi> and <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: remorſe</hi> hath an eye of all ſins paſt, and <hi>tenderneſs</hi> hath an eye on all ſins to come; by <hi>remorſe</hi> is bred ſorrow for ſin, and loathing of ſin; no ſooner he conſiders how by his manifold ſins he hath offended God, crucified Chriſt, grieved the holy Spirit, but his heart bleeds and breaks that he hath done ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly againſt ſo gracious a God: this ſorrow for ſin brings with it a loathing of ſin; he cannot but hate it, that hath cauſed his heart break, yea he hates it, and hates the very thought of it; every look-back is a new addition of deteſtation, and every medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation makes the wound of his <hi>remorſe</hi> to bleed again and again: by <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of conſcience is bred a care and watchfulneſs to avoid ſin to come, for no ſooner is ſin preſented to his conſcience, but he ſtartles at its ſight, and thinks on its vanity, and meditates on that ſtrict and general account he muſt one day make for it; which thoughts and ſin put together in the ballance, he dares not do wickedly for a world of gain: and you may obſerve it, this tenderneſs (or eaſineſs to bleed at the apprehenſion of ſin) is proper and peculiar to that conſcience alone that is illightned, and ſanctified, and purged by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the <hi>affections</hi> muſt be renewed, and that is done by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them upon right objects. I ſhall inſtance in ſome of them, as <hi>love, hatred, hope, fear, joy, ſorrow. Love</hi> I place firſt, which in the unregenerate man is faſtened inordinately upon the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and as one ſin begets another, ſo on whatſoever object it fall, it begets ſome ſin: thus the love of honor breeds ambition, love of riches breeds covetouſneſs, love of beauty breeds luſt, love of pleaſure breeds ſenſuality: whatſoever he <hi>loves</hi> (the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30627:13"/>being earthly) it brings with it ſome ſin, and thereby (the worſt of all) he wickedly prefers earth before heaven, a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill before paradiſe, a few bitter-ſweet pleaſures for an inch of time, before unmixed and immeaſurable joys world without end: But the regenerate man ſettles his <hi>love</hi> upon other objects; as he that is carnal, mindes things carnal, ſo he that is ſpiritual, loves things ſpiritual; no ſooner is he turned (by a ſound and univerſal change of the whole man) <hi>from darkneſs to light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 26.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and from the power of Satan unto God,</hi> but he preſently begins to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with ſome ſweet contentment, upon the flowers of paradiſe, heavenly glimpſes, ſaving graces, and his infinite <hi>love</hi> runs higher and higher, till it imbrace him that dwells in the higheſt, God Almighty; and how ſweet is that love that caſts it ſelf wholly into the boſom of his Maker? how bleſſed is that man, that yearns, and melts, and cleaves, and ſticks unto his gracious God? why, this is right <hi>love,</hi> and for this is the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,
<note place="margin">Cant. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The righteous love thee,</hi> or as others tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, <hi>amat in rectitudinibus, ſhe loves thee righteouſly,</hi> her love is ſet upon the right object,
<note place="margin">Pſal 119 165. 1 Theſſ. 5.13.</note> God: not that the regenerate loves nothing elſe, for he loves <hi>the Law, the Miniſters,</hi> and all the ordinances of God appointed for his good, but whatſoever he loves, it reflects upon God, he <hi>loves</hi> all for God, and God for himſelf.</p>
               <p>The ſecond affection is <hi>hatred,</hi> which in the unregenerate is ſo inordinate,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.30.</note> that he is <hi>an hater of God, Rom.</hi> 1.30. not that he hates God in himſelf (for God is univerſally good, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hated) but in ſome particular reſpect, becauſe he reſtrains him from his pleaſure, or puniſheth him for his ſin, or croſſeth his lewd appetites by his holy commands: And as he hates God, ſo likewiſe his brother,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.11.</note> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.11. Hence ariſe thoſe envies, emulations, jars, contentions amongſt thoſe that profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.6.</note> of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> could ſay, <hi>A brother goeth to law with a brother,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.6. But of all <hi>brethren</hi> he hates them moſt, of whom our Savior is the <hi>firſt-born:</hi> Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ones ever were,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29. Iſa. 8.18.</note> and ever will be <hi>ſigns, and wonders, and monſters unto many; a ſcorn, reproach and deriſion to them that are round about them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 71.7. Pſal 79.4.</note> But he that is regenerate hates ſin, and in whomſoever ſin rules or reigns, he cannot but hate them, <hi>Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee?</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) and, <hi>Am
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30627:13"/>not I grieved with thoſe that riſe up againſt thee?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.21.</note> Not that <hi>David,</hi> or any Saint of God, hates the perſon of any one, but ſin in the perſon, or he is ſaid to hate them for ſins ſake that is in them; in this reſpect he bids them defiance in the verſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, <hi>I hate them with a perfect hatred,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>I count them mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> Pſal. 139.22. I know there is a perpetual combate in the regenerate, betwixt the fleſh and the Spirit, and therefore we muſt underſtand this <hi>hatred,</hi> which <hi>David</hi> calls <hi>a perfect hatred,</hi> according to the perfection in <hi>parts,</hi> but not in <hi>degrees:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Intenſivè, non extenſivè.</note> never any but Chriſt hated ſin to the full, with all his ſtrength, and with all his might, but in ſome meaſure his ſervants hatred is <hi>perfect,</hi> which makes him always hate ſin in others, and often in himſelf, when after the commiſſion of any evil, he begins to repent him,
<note place="margin">Iob 42.6.</note> and <hi>to abhor himſelf</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> did) <hi>in duſt and aſhes,</hi> Job 42.6.</p>
               <p>The third affection is <hi>Hope</hi> (this I rather name then <hi>deſire,</hi> becauſe whatſoever we <hi>Hope</hi> for, we cannot but deſire it, and ſo it is implyed in it) now this <hi>Hope</hi> in the unregenerate is faſtened on <hi>this world, and the things of this world,</hi> he <hi>hopes</hi> for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, riches, or the like; as for his <hi>hope</hi> of Heaven, it is but a waking mans dream; a dream, ſaid I? Yes,
<note place="margin">Somnium vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantium.</note> as dreams in the night fill us with illuſions and vain forms (you know a Beggar may dream he is a King) ſo <hi>hope</hi> abuſing the imagination of the unregenerate, fills their ſouls many a time with vain or empty contentments; but the <hi>hope</hi> of the regenerate both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys the right object, and right means; his eye is fixt on future good, and he endeavors to purſue it, till he get the poſſeſſion; if in the purſuit he meet with croſſes, loſſes, griefs, diſgraces, ſickneſſes, or any other calamities, his <hi>hope</hi> is able to ſweeten the bittereſt miſery that can poſſibly befal him; <hi>the afflictions of this life</hi> bid him look for a better, a croſs here mindes him of the glory above; and howſoever this <hi>Hope</hi> may have many difficulties and wraſtlings in him (therefore it is compared to an anchor, which holds the ſhip in a ſtorm, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19.) yet it holds and ſticks ſo firm in God and his promiſes, that he is confident, that after this life an heavenly crown ſhall be ſet on his head, by the hands of God and his Angels.</p>
               <p>The fourth affection is <hi>fear,</hi> which in the unregenerate is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worldly or ſervile: If it faſten on the world, then he <hi>fears</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:30627:14"/>the loſs of his credit, or of his profit, and becauſe he and the world muſt part at laſt, he <hi>fears</hi> this ſeparation above all fears: <hi>O death</hi> (ſaith the wiſeman) <hi>how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that liveth at reſt in his poſſeſsions, unto the man that hath nothing to vex him, and that hath prosperity in all things?</hi> Ecclus.
<note place="margin">Ecclus. 41.1.</note> 41.1. O theſe thoughts of the griſly forms, and ugly face of death, of the parting from all worldly pleaſures for ever, of his rotting in the grave, dragging to the Tribunal and Terror of the laſt day, they cannot but make his heart to ſhrug toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for horror, and (many time) to quake and tremble like an Aſpine-leaf; or if his fear reflect on God, then is it a ſervile fear; for as the ſervant or hireling works not for love of his maſter, but onely for <hi>fear</hi> of puniſhment; or as the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous woman is afraid of her husband, not out of love or affection, but leſt he reward her to her foul demerits; ſo he <hi>fears</hi> God for fear of puniſhment due unto him from God: It is otherwiſe with the man that is <hi>born again,</hi> his fear is either initial or filial in pangs of the new birth,
<note place="margin">Weems.</note> or in the new born babe it is called initial, becauſe then he caſts away ſin both out of Gods love, to which he hath partly attained, and out of the woful effects of ſin, which he hath throughly conſidered; with the right eye he beholds God, and with the left eye he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds puniſhment; ſo that this fear is a middle (as it were) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>ſervile and filial fear,</hi> and as the needle draweth in the threed, ſo this <hi>fear</hi> draweth in <hi>charity,</hi> and makes way for <hi>filial fear;</hi> to which, if by growth in grace he be fully ripened, then he <hi>fears</hi> God out of love to God, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 33.6.</note> 
                  <hi>The fear of the Lord is his treaſure,</hi> Iſa. 33.6. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was treaſure more dear to the worldings, then is Gods <hi>fear</hi> to him, his love of God, his <hi>deſire</hi> to pleaſe God, and his <hi>fear</hi> of being ſeparated from God, keeps him in ſuch awe, that though no puniſhment, no death, no hell were at all, yet he would not ſin wickedly, wilfully and maliciouſly, for a world of treaſures.</p>
               <p>The fifth affection is <hi>joy,</hi> which in the unregenerate is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſual and bruitiſh; it hath no better objects then gold, or greatneſs, or offices, or honors, or the like: and what are all theſe but a ſhadow, a ſhip, a bird, an arrow, a poſt that paſſeth by? or rather, <hi>as crackling of thorns under a pot,</hi> as flaſhes of lightning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30627:14"/>before everlaſting fire? But the <hi>joy</hi> of the regenerate is a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>joy,</hi> and the matter of it is the light of Gods countenance, or the robe of Chriſts righteouſneſs, or the promiſes of Gods word; or above all, God Almighty, bleſſed evermore: Thus <hi>David, Whom have I in heaven but thee?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.25.</note> 
                  <hi>and there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee,</hi> Pſal. 73.25. Why, this is that <hi>joy</hi> which no man can concieve, but he that enjoyes it; this is that <hi>white ſtone,</hi> Rev. 2.17.
<note place="margin">Revel. 2.17.</note> whoſe ſplendor ſhines onely upon heavenly hearts; this is that glimpſe of heavens glory, which ſpringing up in a ſanctified heart, out of the wells of ſalvation, and carried along with addition of freſh comforts (from the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments) through a fruitful current and courſe of mans life, it is at laſt entertained into the boundleſs and bottomleſs Ocean of the <hi>joyes</hi> of Heaven. I will not ſay, but ſometimes it may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, and ſtopped with ſome doubts, or diſtruſts, or weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of degree, yet in reſpect of its creation, or eſſence,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Boltons</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with God.</note> or bliſsful iſſue, it is (ſaith one) <hi>a very glimpſe of heaven, a pure taſte of the rivers of life, and firſt fruits</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>of everlaſting joyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſixth affection is <hi>ſorrow,</hi> which in the unregenerate is a worldly <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and the effects of it are death; ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>The ſorrow of the world worketh death,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> In this kinde how endleſs are the <hi>ſorrows</hi> of men for their loſſes, or croſſes, that ſometimes may befall them? And howſoever ſome may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to comfort them in Chriſt, they are ſo dead-hearted that nothing can perſwade, nothing relliſh with them that concerns heaven, or ſalvation. But in the regenerate, ſorrow looks up to Godwards, not that the beholding of God in himſelf can bring <hi>ſorrow</hi> to a man, for he is a moſt comfortable object, which made <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>The light of thy countenance — is gladneſs to my heart:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.6, 7.</note> but the beholding of ſin, which hindreth from the cleer ſight of that object, this is it which breeds <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and this the Apoſtle calls <hi>godly ſorrow, working repentance to ſalvation, not to be repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. It is not every <hi>ſorrow,</hi> but <hi>godly ſorrow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10. V. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>I rejoyce</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>not that ye were made ſorry, but that ye ſorrowed to repentance:</hi> And would you know who <hi>ſorrows</hi> to repentance? it is he, and onely he that groans and ſighs under the heavy weight and burthen of his ſins, that is of a broken and contrite heart, that trembles at Gods word, that is grieved at his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30627:15"/>enormities, that forſakes all ſins, and that reſigns up himſelf in all holy obedience to Gods bleſſed will; this <hi>ſorrow</hi> is a bleſſed <hi>ſorrow</hi> that brings forth joy and immortality: Therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ye, comfort ye all that mourn in Sion, what though for a night (in pangs of <hi>the new birth</hi>) you lye ſorrowing and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your ſins? mark a while, and the day will dawn, <hi>ride on, becauſe of the word of truth,</hi> and a day ſtar will ariſe in your hearts that will never ſet; nay weep &amp; weep again, till you can ſay with <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>All the night make I my bed to ſwim</hi> with my tears, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the Sun of righteouſneſs will appear, and he will dry away your tears, and ſhine upon you with everlaſting light. Certainly thus is it with every regenerate man, <hi>he loves, and hates, and hopes, and fears, and joyes, and ſorrows,</hi> and all theſe paſſions are renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him: To give inſtance in one, <hi>David</hi> for all the regenerate, his <hi>love</hi> appears Pſal.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.47.130.22.62 5.</note> 119.47. <hi>My delight ſhall be in thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments which I have loved:</hi> his <hi>hatred</hi> appears Pſal. 130.22. <hi>I hate thy enemies with a perfect hatred.</hi> His <hi>hope</hi> appears Pſal. 62.5. <hi>My ſoul wait thou onely upon God, for my expectation is from him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">119 120.119.16.162.</note> His <hi>fear</hi> appears Pſal. 119.120. <hi>His Judgments are terrible, I tremble and quake.</hi> His <hi>joy</hi> appears Pſal. 119.16. <hi>Thy Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are my delight, I rejoyce in them as one that findeth great ſpoils.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">119.136.</note> His <hi>ſorrow</hi> appears Pſal. 119.136. <hi>Mine eyes guſh out with rivers of water.</hi> Here is <hi>Love, and Hatred, and Hope, and Fear, and Joy, and Sorrow,</hi> and all are ſet upon their right ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al objects.</p>
               <q>You ſee now a pourtraiture of the <hi>new man,</hi> which ſhould be the caſe of all men; my text ſaith indefinitely <hi>A man</hi>] im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying every <hi>man,</hi> and every part of <hi>man;</hi> every man ſhould be regenerated, every part of man ſhould be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and whereas <hi>man</hi> conſiſts on two parts, the body and ſoul, all the members of his body, <hi>the Heart, the Eye, the Ear, the Tongue</hi> in eſpecial; all the powers of his ſoul, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, the Will, the Memory, the Conſcience, the Affections</hi> in general, all muſt be renewed, and the whole <hi>man] born again.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And yet (beloved) I mean not ſo, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> as that a man renewed is never overcome with ſin, I know there is in him <hi>a continual fight</hi> betwixt the fleſh and the ſpirit, each of which ſtriveth to make his part ſtrong againſt the other, and ſometimes <hi>Amalek</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:30627:15"/>prevails, and ſometimes Iſrael prevails; ſometimes his <hi>heart</hi> falls a luſting, his <hi>eyes</hi> a wandring, his <hi>ears</hi> a tickling, his <hi>tongue</hi> a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; ſometimes his <hi>underſtanding</hi> errs, his <hi>will</hi> rebells, his <hi>memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> fails, his <hi>conſcience</hi> ſleeps, and his <hi>affections</hi> turn the ſtream after ſenſual objects; but (that which differs him from the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man) if he ſin, it is with a gracious reluctation, he reſiſts it to the uttermoſt of his abilities, and if at laſt he commit ſin through the violence of tentation, ſubduing the infirmity of the fleſh, he is preſently abaſhed, and then begins he to ſet repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance a work in all the parts and powers of his body and ſoul; then begins his <hi>conſcience</hi> to trouble him within, and will never be at quiet until the ciſtern of his <hi>heart</hi> (being overcharged) hath cauſed his <hi>eyes,</hi> the flood-gates, with moiſt ſinful humors, to overflow the cheeks with tears of contrition, and thus he is <hi>waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, juſtified, ſanctified,</hi> and reſtored to his former integrity again.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9.</note> Examine then your ſelves, you that deſire heaven at your ends, would you inherit the Kingdom? would you live with Angels? would you ſave your ſouls? examine and try whether your <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſouls</hi> be ſanctified throughout, and if you have no ſenſe or feeling of the <hi>new birth</hi> (for 'tis a myſtery to the unregenerate) then never look to ſee (in that ſtate) <hi>the kingdom of God;</hi> but if you perceive the working of ſaving grace effectually in you, (and you cannot but perceive it if you have it) if you feel the power of godlineſs firſt ſeizing the <hi>heart,</hi> and after diſperſing it ſelf over all the parts and powers of <hi>body and ſoul:</hi> (or yet more in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular) if your <hi>hearts</hi> be ſoftned by the Spirit, if <hi>your eyes wait upon God,</hi> if your ears liſten to his word, if <hi>your tongues ſhew forth his praiſe,</hi> if your <hi>underſtanding</hi> attain to ſaving knowledge, if your <hi>wills</hi> conform to the <hi>will</hi> of God, if your <hi>memories</hi> be ſtored with heavenly doctrine, if your <hi>conſciences</hi> be tender and ſenſible of the leaſt ſin whatſoever, if you <hi>love</hi> that which is good, if you <hi>hate that which is evil,</hi> if you <hi>hope</hi> for the bleſſings above, if you <hi>fear him that can deſtroy both body and ſoul;</hi> in a word, if you <hi>joy</hi> in goodneſs, if you <hi>ſorrow</hi> for ſin, then are you <hi>born again.</hi> Happy man in this caſe that ever he was <hi>born,</hi> and thus every man muſt be, or he cannot be happy: <hi>Except a man</hi>] (every man, every part of man) <hi>be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far of the ſubject, <hi>man</hi>] we come now to the act, or deed to be done, he muſt <hi>be born again.</hi>]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:30627:16"/>
               <head>Be born again.]</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe children are brought to the birth,</hi> and leſt the ſaying be true of us, <hi>there is no ſtrength to bring forth:</hi> I ſhall now (by Gods aſſiſtance) proceed to the <hi>birth</hi> it ſelf.
<note place="margin">2 King. 19.3.</note> Here we have the maner of it, and we may obſerve a double maner,</p>
               <p>Firſt, of the words containing <hi>the new birth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, of <hi>the new birth</hi> contained in the words.</p>
               <p>The maner of the words apears in the original <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] two words, and either of them hath its diverſe reading. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Valla</hi> would rather have to be <hi>genitus, begotten; Except a man be begotten.</hi>] Others uſually ſay <hi>natus, born; Except a man be born.</hi>] And as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſome would have to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>above,</hi> or <hi>from heaven; Except a man be born from above.</hi>] Others uſually <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>again; Except a man be born again.</hi>] <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> cites both theſe, and of each reading we ſhall gather ſomething for our own inſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except a man be regenerated,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eraſm. annot. in loc.</note> 
                  <hi>or begotten</hi> (ſaith <hi>Valla</hi>) <hi>As man that is born of a woman is begotten of a man, ſo he that is born again,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>muſt have a begetting too:</hi> and therefore ſometimes it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>renaſcentia, a new birth,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>regeneratio, a new be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting,</hi> or <hi>regeneration.</hi> If you ask of whom is the new man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten? Saint <hi>Iames</hi> tells you, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Of his own will begat he us with the word of truth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.18.</note> The former words note the impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive cauſe, theſe latter the inſtrument, it was <hi>God</hi> that <hi>begat us,</hi> and with the <hi>ſeed of the word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>God begat us,</hi> and ſo are we called <hi>Gods ſons, born not of blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God,</hi> John 1.13. Regeneration is the work of God, and becauſe it is a work external, it is therefore communicable to each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity: <hi>Ye are ſanctified</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>in the name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and by the spirit of our God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11. The Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, all ſanctifie, all work the ſame work: but as in the Godhead there is but one Eſſence, and yet three maners of being of the ſame one Eſſence; ſo in Gods outward operations, all the Perſons work <hi>rem eandem,</hi> one thing, but all work not <hi>eodem modo,</hi> after one maner: For inſtance, the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30627:16"/>works of Creation, Redemption, and Sanctification, are the common works of God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, yet every one of theſe works common to all three, are terminated in ſome one of them: So the
<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.6.</note> Father is ſaid to create, the
<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 1.10.</note> Son is ſaid to create, the
<note n="c" place="margin">Iob 26.13.</note> Holy Ghoſt is ſaid to create; ſo the Father is ſaid to redeem, the Son is ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem, the Holy Ghoſt is ſaid to redeem; ſo the Father is ſaid to ſanctifie, the Son is ſaid to ſanctifie, the Holy Ghoſt is ſaid to ſanctifie: Thus all three concur to every one of theſe works, and yet every one of theſe works, is terminated, ſpecified, and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as it were) in the very laſt act by one of theſe three: The work of the Creation is determinated immediately in God the Father, the work of Redemption is determinated immediately in God the Son, the work of Regeneration is determinated immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in God the Holy Ghoſt. And it is memorable, that as the community of theſe works <hi>(ad extra)</hi> depends on the unity of Gods Eſſence, ſo the diverſity of their determinations depends on the diverſe maners of Gods exiſtence, or ſubſiſting: the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of himſelf, neither made nor begotten, and therefore it beſt agrees with him to make all things of nothing, which is the work of <hi>Creation;</hi> the Son is of the Father alone by reflection of his intellect, and ſo called the repreſentation of his Fathers Image, and therefore it beſt agrees with him to repreſent his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers mercies to mankinde, by ſaving them from death and hell, which is the work of <hi>Redemption;</hi> the Holy Ghoſt is of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, proceeding (and as it were breathed) from them both by the act of the will, and therefore it beſt agrees with him <hi>(that bloweth where he liſteth)</hi> to blow on our wills, and by his breath to purge and purifie us, which is the work of <hi>Regeneration.</hi> To ſum up all in a word, this work of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (or Sanctification, or whatever elſe you will call it) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the work, it is of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, but in reſpect of the laſt act, it is of the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.6, 8.</note> and not of the Father, nor the Son; and thus our Savior concludes, Joh. 3.8. <hi>That which is born of the spirit, is spirit, and ſo is every man that is born of the spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, as Gods Spirit is the principal, ſo Gods Word is the inſtrumental cauſe of our Regeneration. <hi>Ye are born again</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorruptible by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30627:17"/>word of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23. 1 Iohn 1.1. Rom. 10.17. Rom. 11.10.</note> 
                  <hi>which liveth and abideth for ever,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.23. this word St. <hi>John</hi> calls <hi>the word of life,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> the producer of faith, and <hi>the power of God unto ſalvation;</hi> yea this word <hi>is quick and powerful, and ſharper then any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and spirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart,</hi> Heb.
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> 4.12. they that are <hi>born again,</hi> cannot but remember how <hi>quick,</hi> and <hi>powerful,</hi> and <hi>ſharp,</hi> Gods word was at their Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: firſt, like an hammer it beat on their hearts till it broke them all to pieces, and then like a ſword, by a terrible, cutting, piercing power, it ſtruck a ſhaking and trembling into the very center of their ſouls; laſt of all like oyl (when, as the man in the <hi>Gospel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 10.30.</note> they were wounded indeed) it began to ſupple thoſe wounds, and to heal the bruiſes, and to refreſh the weak and tender heart with all the promiſes of God revealed in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And thus a man being begotten of the Spirit with <hi>the word of truth,</hi> he comes at laſt to the birth: So we read, <hi>Except a man be born.</hi>] And this I ſuppoſe to be fuller then the other, becauſe a <hi>begetting</hi> may be, and no <hi>birth</hi> follow, as many that are ſtifled in the womb, are <hi>begotten,</hi> not <hi>born;</hi> but if the <hi>birth</hi> be, it doth preſuppoſe a <hi>begetting,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> and ſo it implyes it: <hi>Except a man be born,</hi> that is, <hi>except a man be begotten and born, he cannot ſee Gods kingdom.</hi> If you ask of whom born? I anſwer, as God is <hi>Father,</hi> ſo the Church is the <hi>Mother</hi> of every childe of God: to this purpoſe ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Jeruſalem which is above is free, which is the mother of us all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> Gal. 4.26. what is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> but the Church?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.5.</note> for as that City was the ſeat of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 122.5. ſo is this Church the throne of Chriſt, figured by the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.7. and therefore of both theſe God thus proclaims, <hi>Here ſhall be my reſt for ever, here will I dwell, for I have a delight herein,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.</note> Pſal. 132.14. And rightly is the Church called our <hi>mother,</hi> firſt becauſe ſhe is the ſpouſe of our <hi>Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troathed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19. Cant. 6.3.</note> Hoſea 2.19. coupled and made <hi>one,</hi> Cant. 6.3. <hi>I am my welbeloveds, and my welbeloved is mine;</hi> and ſecondly, becauſe we are children born of her; this teacheth us to honor our mother, and like little children to hang at her breaſts for our ſuſtenance; <hi>Suck,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 66.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her conſolations, milk out, and be delighted with the abundance of her glory.</hi> It is the Church that brings forth children to God by the miniſtry of his word,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30627:17"/>and if we are children of this mother, we muſt feed on that milk which flows from her two breaſts, the Old and New Teſtament; <hi>As new born babes</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>deſire the ſincere milk of the Word, that ye may grow thereby,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.2. In a word,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> out of the Church there is no ſalvation: <hi>who have not the Church their mother, cannot have God their Father,</hi> was the ſaying of old; and good reaſon, for out of the Church there is no means of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no word to teach, no ſacraments to confirm, but all theſe, and all other means are in the womb of the Church: it is here, and here onely, where the ſpirit of <hi>immortal ſeed</hi> begets grace in the heart, and ſo a man is <hi>born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] ſome read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>from heaven,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>] and ſo the words run, <hi>Except a man be born from above</hi>] <hi>From above it is that every good &amp; perfect gift cometh: Aman can receive nothing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.27.</note> 
                  <hi>except it be given him from heaven,</hi> Joh. 3.27. But how then ſaith our Savior of the wind (to which he compareth <hi>every one that is born of the Spirit</hi>) that we know not <hi>whence it cometh, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it goeth?</hi> I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> this <hi>[whence]</hi> reſpects more the cauſe then place, we know the wind comes from the South, or North, or Eaſt, or Weſt, but why ſo and ſo, we cannot tell; we know the Spirit is above, and the <hi>new birth</hi> or regeneration comes from the Spirit: But <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> why it is ſo, or what moves the Spirit to do ſo, beſides his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the good pleaſure of his will,</hi> we cannot tell.</p>
               <p>Or if we read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as others do,
<note place="margin">Beda, &amp; Eraſm. paraph. in loc.</note> the words then run thus, <hi>Except a man be born again.</hi>] To this <hi>Nicodemus's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſeems more direct, <hi>How can a man be born when he is old? can he enter the ſecond time into his mothers womb?</hi> No queſtion he took Chriſts <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pro</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, onely thus he miſtook, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond birth ſhould be after the maner of the firſt birth, and therefore he ſaith, <hi>Can a man that is old</hi> (ſuch as he himſelf was) <hi>be born again?</hi> No, ſaith our Savior, <hi>that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh,</hi> and there is but one <hi>birth</hi> after this maner; but to <hi>be born again</hi>] is to be born after the Spirit, and this is that ſecond birth: <hi>A man is firſt born of the fleſh,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>and he muſt be again born of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence appears the difference of the firſt and ſecond birth; the firſt birth is of the <hi>earth, earthy;</hi> the ſecond birth is <hi>of the Lord from heaven, heavenly;</hi> the firſt birth is of nature, full of ſin; the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30627:18"/>ſecond is of grace, full of ſanctity: the firſt birth is originally of fleſh and blood, the ſecond birth is originally of the <hi>Spirit and water:</hi> In a word, the firſt birth kills, the ſecond gives life; generation loſt us, it muſt be <hi>regeneration</hi> that recovers us: O bleſſed birth, without which no birth is happy, in compariſon of which (though it were to be born heir of the whole world) all is but miſery!
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.24.</note> this was <hi>Moſes</hi> praiſe, that <hi>he eſteemed the reproach of Chriſt above all the treaſures in Egypt,</hi> rather would he be the ſon of God, then to <hi>be called the ſon of Pharaohs daughter,</hi> Heb. 11.24. No queſtion it is a great dignity to be <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſon in Law to a King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.23 <hi>Polan Syntag. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 37. Act. 8.37. Acts 10.47. Acts 16.14. Titus 2.5.</note> but nothing in compariſon of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Son of God: this ſonſhip is that degree, above which there needs no aſpiring, and under which there is no happineſs, no heaven, no <hi>kingdom: Except a man be born again</hi>] <hi>he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Thus far of the maner of the words, which containing the <hi>new birth,</hi> it appears in them, the father of it is God, the ſeed of it the Word, the mother of it the Church, the place of it, whence? from Heaven: the time of it, when? after a man is once born, then he muſt be <hi>again born: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man be born again.</hi>]</q>
               <p>Secondly, as you ſee the maner of the <hi>words</hi> containing <hi>the new birth,</hi> ſo now ſee the maner of <hi>the new birth</hi> contained in the <hi>words.</hi> I know it is not wrought in all after one maner, nor is the maner known to us, but onely ſo far forth as it is ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in us, and therefore we muſt conſider man before baptiſm, in baptiſm, after baptiſm.</p>
               <p>In ſome is <hi>the new birth</hi> wrought <hi>before baptiſm,</hi> as in the eunuch, under <hi>Candace</hi> Queen of the <hi>Aethiopians, Acts</hi> 8.37. and in the Captain <hi>Cornelius,</hi> together with his kinſmen and and near friends, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47. and in <hi>Lydia, Acts</hi> 16.14. and ſo our charity tells us, that every Infant dying before baptiſm, is renewed by the Spirit: but the maner of this working we know not, for it is one of the ſecrets of the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>In others is <hi>the new birth</hi> wrought <hi>in Baptiſm,</hi> which indeed is the Sacrament of <hi>the new birth,</hi> and ſeal of <hi>Regeneration;</hi> but howſoever in <hi>Paedo-Baptiſm</hi> we ſee the outward ſeal, yet we ſee not, we feel not the maner of the inward working; for this alſo is the ſecret of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>de Sacram. Baptiſm. c</hi> 10. <hi>habent fidem habitualem.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Field</hi> concerning the Author of the grounds of the old and new Religion. S. 2. <hi>Fides eſt in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantibus poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi> Urſinus <hi>parte ſecunda Catechiſ. queſt.</hi> 74. <hi>Spiritus operatur in potentiis animae ipſorum ut Bellar: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beut spiritum fidei.</hi> Zanch. in cap. 2. ad Epheſ.</note> ſpirit of God.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:30627:18"/>
               <p>In others is <hi>the new birth</hi> wrought <hi>after Baptiſm;</hi> ſo <hi>Polanus:</hi> but whether <hi>after Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>in Baptiſm,</hi> we will not diſpute, onely (as the caſe ſtands with us) this I affirm, That there is no manifeſtation of <hi>the new birth,</hi> until after Baptiſm. But when after Baptiſm? I anſwer, whenſoever men receive Chriſt by faith, which though it be many years after, yet then do they feel the power of God regenerate them, and to work all things in them, which he offered in Baptiſm. Now the maner of this feeling (or of Gods Spirit working) proceeds uſually thus:</p>
               <p>There be certain ſteps of degrees (ſay Divines) by which it paſſeth, and howſoever in thoſe whom God hath bleſſed with that great favor of holy and Chriſtian education (the Spirit of God dropping grace into their hearts, even very betimes) theſe ſteps, or degrees, are not ſo eaſily perceived: Yet in thoſe men who have lived long in ſin, whoſe ſins have been groſs, and great and grievous, no ſooner come they to a <hi>new birth,</hi> but they can feel grace work in them ſtep after ſtep, and theſe ſteps we ſhall reckon to the number of eight.</p>
               <p>The firſt is a <hi>ſight</hi> of ſin, and this our Savior reckons for the firſt work of the Spirit, <hi>When he is come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 16.8.</note> 
                  <hi>he will reprove the world of ſin,</hi> John 16.8. Of ſin? how? why thus: no ſooner begins this bleſſed change from nature to grace, but the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (wrought on by Gods word) opens its book, and preſents to the ſoul a bed-roll of thoſe many, mighty, hainous ſins, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt God and man, there he may read in bloody burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lines the abominations of his youth, the ſins of all his life; and to bring them into method, the Commandments of God ſtand as a remembrancer before his eyes: the firſt tells him of his loving ſomewhat above God: the ſecond, of his worſhipping a falſe God, or the true God after a falſe maner: the third, of his diſhonoring the great and mighty name of God: the fourth, of his breaking the Lords days, either in doing the works of the fleſh, or leaving undone the works of the Spirit; nor is this all: as againſt God, ſo againſt his neighbor hath he ſinned: the fifth tells him of his ſtubbornneſs and diſobedience: the ſixth, of his paſſions, and deſire of revenge: the ſeventh, of his lewdneſs and luſtful courſes: the eighth, of his robberies and covetous thefts: the ninth, of his lyes and and ſlanders, back-bitings and raſh judgements: the tenth, of his covetous thoughts, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30627:19"/>of the heart to all maner of evil. Good Lord! what a number of evils, yea, what innumerable ſwarms of lawleſs thoughts, and words, and actions doth he read in his conſcience? But above all, his darling-delight, his beloved ſin is writ in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt characters, this he findes to have bewitched him moſt, and to have domineered above all the reſt in his waſted conſcience; this ſin in ſome is worldlineſs, wantonneſs, uſury, pride, revenge, or the like; in others it is drunkenneſs, gluttony, gaming, ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril jeſting, ſymony, or the like; whatſoever it is, the conſcience tells him of it again and again; where that he may read it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his other ſins, the Spirit of God now opens the eyes of his minde, and lets him ſee the very mud and filth of his ſoul, that lay at the bottom before unſeen, and undiſcerned. Thus is the firſt working of the new life, to wit, a feeling of the old death of his ſoul in ſins and treſpaſſes; and here the axiome is true, no <hi>generation without corruption,</hi> a man muſt firſt feel this death, before he is <hi>born again.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſtep is, <hi>Senſe of divine wrath,</hi> which begets in him fear;
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>The spirit of bondage begets fear,</hi> Rom. 8.15. and thus it works: no ſooner hath the man a ſight and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his ſin, but then Gods Spirit (now called <hi>the spirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi>) preſents to him the armory of Gods flaming wrath, and fiery indignation; this makes him to feel (as if he were pricked with the ſtroak of an arrow, or point of a ſword, or ſting of an Adder) that he is a moſt curſed and damnable creature, juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerving all the miſeries of this life, and all the fiery torments of hell in that life to come; yea, this makes him tremble, and ſtand, and look, as if he were throughly frighted with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry countenance of God Almighty: Would you view him in this caſe? his conſcience hath now awaked him out of his dead ſenſual ſleep, by the Trumpet of the Law, his heart is now ſcorched with the ſecret ſenſe of Gods angry face, his ſoul is now full ſorely cruſhed under the moſt grievous burthen of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable ſins, his thoughts are now full of fear and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as if no leſs then very hell and horror were ready to ſeize upon his body and ſoul. I ſay not what meaſure of this wrath is poured on all men in their converſion; for I ſuppoſe ſome feel more, and ſome have leſs of it; but I verily believe, ſome there are that (in theſe pangs of <hi>the new birth</hi>) have been ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30627:19"/>(as it were) with the very flames of hell, inſomuch that they might truly ſay with <hi>David, Gods wrath lieth hard upon me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 88.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and he hath afflicted me with all his waves,</hi> Pſal. 88.7. And no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for this is the time of fear; now it is that Satan ſtrives bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to ſtifle <hi>the new man</hi> in the womb, and therefore he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diminiſhed his ſins, and made them appear little or nothing in his eyes, when he once ſees the man ſmitten down <hi>into the place of dragons, and covered with the ſhadow of death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.19.</note> then he puts into his minde his innumerable ſins, and (that which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately follows) the curſe of the Law, and the wrath of God, which he yet makes more griſly and fierce, with a purpoſe to plunge him into the bottomleſs pit of horror and deſpair. By this means he perſwaded <hi>Cain</hi> to cry out (when he was in this caſe) <hi>My puniſhment is greater then I can bear;</hi> or,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> as others tranſlate, <hi>Mine iniquity is greater then can be forgiven,</hi> Gen. 4.13. And therefore thus far the unregenerate goes with the man <hi>born again,</hi> both have a ſight of ſin, and ſenſe of wrath, but here they part; for the man unregenerate either ſinks under it, or labors to allay it with worldly comforts, or ſome counterfeit calm: but <hi>the man born again,</hi> is onely humbled by it, and ſeeks the right way to cure it, and at laſt (by the help of Gods Spirit) he paſſeth quite through it, I mean, through this hell upon earth, into the ſpiritual pleaſures of the Kingdom of grace, which is to <hi>be born again.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The third ſtep is <hi>Sorrow for ſin,</hi> and this is more peculiar to Gods childe; there is a ſorrow which is a common work of grace, which an hypocrite may have; and there is a ſorrow which is a work of ſpecial grace, and this likewiſe precedes the exerciſe of faith.</p>
               <p>But ſome object, Chriſt muſt work this ſorrow, or it is good for nothing; now if Chriſt be in the ſoul working ſorrow, then there is faith, therefore faith muſt go before ſorrow.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, although it is true that Chriſt cannot be in the ſoul, but in the ſame inſtant there is the habit of faith; yet it follows not that faith is before ſorrow, for the habits of theſe graces are both together, and at once in the ſoul; or howſoever, it follows not that the ſoul is inabled by an act of faith to apply Chriſt to it ſelf as ſoon as Chriſt is in the ſoul, or as ſoon as the habit of faith is infuſed into the ſoul: The queſtion is, whether the ſoul in reſpect of us (who can onely judge of the habit by the act)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30627:20"/>cannot be ſaid to have ſorrow or repentance before faith? the queſtion is not, which the ſoul hath firſt in reſpect of Gods gift, but which it acts firſt for our apprehenſion? Surely to us it firſt ſorrows for ſin, and then it acts or exerciſeth faith by coming to Chriſt, and relying upon Chriſt for Salvation, &amp;c. he grieves not onely becauſe he fears he muſt be damned (ſo <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> might) but becauſe he knows he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be damned: this is the more eſpecial object of his ſorrow, in that he is ſo wicked, ſo ſinful, ſo rebellious, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God: this ſin, I ſay, is it (wherein he was conceived, and born, wherein he hath lived, and continued) that makes him ſob, and ſigh, and ſorrow, and mourn; and yet this ſorrow is ſometimes taken largely for the whole work of converſion; ſometimes ſtrictly for conviction, contrition, and humiliation; in like maner repentance is taken ſometimes largely, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtrictly: By this diſtinction it may eaſily appear how ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row goes before repentance, and how repentance goes before faith. Indeed, for the latter is the great controverſie, but ſome reconcile it thus: Repentance hath two parts, the averſion of the ſoul from Sin, and the converſion of the ſoul to God; the latter part of it is onely an effect of faith, the former part of it, <hi>viz.</hi> the turning of the ſoul from Sin is alſo an effect, but not onely an effect; for it is begun before faith, though it be not ended till our life end. Some object, that God works repentance and faith together: But we diſpute not how God works them, but how the ſoul acts them; not which is in the ſoul firſt, but which appears out of the ſoul firſt: neither is it any new thing in Philoſophy to ſay, Thoſe cauſes which produce an effect, though they be in time together, yet are mutually before one another in order of nature, in diverſe reſpects to their ſeveral cauſalities. Thus a man muſt have repentance before he have ſaving and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith; and yet a man muſt have faith before the work of repentance be perfect in the ſoul. As we maintain repentance to be a precedent work; ſo we deny it not to be a ſubſequent effect: Sorrow is before the birth too, as the Apoſtle intimates, 2 Cor.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> 7.10. <hi>Godly ſorrow works repentance,</hi> that is, ſorrow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares a man for repentance, it goes afore it, and prepares for it. And now it is, that Gods ſpirit begins to renew his heart, as God himſelf proclaimeth, <hi>I will put a new spirit within them, and I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30627:20"/>will take the ſtony heart out of their bodies, and will give them an heart of fleſh,</hi> Ezek. 11.19.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 11.19.</note> his heart that before was hard as flint, now begins to relent, and ſoften, and break in pieces:
<note place="margin">Acts 2.37.</note> How ſo? it is Gods Spirit that <hi>pricks the heart,</hi> and this pricking ſoftens it, <hi>Dum pungit, ungit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jorom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieronym.</note> Compunction ſoftens and ſupples the heart, ſo that be it never ſo ſtony, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it becomes <hi>an heart of fleſh;</hi> you know thoſe that are apt to weep, or yern, or ſorrow, we call them <hi>tender-hearted;</hi> you may be ſure then he that is <hi>prickt,</hi> till his heart bleed inwardly, he that weeps blood (which every heart doth that is prickt on this maner) ſure his heart is tender indeed; I ſay, <hi>tender,</hi> for as the very word imports, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) his heart <hi>weeps,</hi> why? his heart is <hi>broken: David</hi> joyns theſe together, <hi>A broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not despiſe,</hi> Pſalm 51.17.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> And no wonder if an heart that is broken, and rent, and wounded, and prickt, falls a weeping blood; well might <hi>David</hi> ſay when he was broken, Pſal. 38.8. (I have wept;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.8.</note> nay more) <hi>I have roared for the very grief</hi> (or diſquietneſs) <hi>of my heart:</hi> and again, <hi>My ſoul</hi> (or my heart) <hi>melteth</hi> (or droppeth) <hi>for very heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Not that his heart dropt indeed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.28.</note> but becauſe the tears which he ſhed, were not drops of water running onely from his eyes (an onion may cauſe ſo much) but iſſuing from his heart; which heart being grieved, and ſore grieved, it is ſaid to be <hi>wounded;</hi> and ſo his tears coming from it, they may be called no leſs then very blood, <hi>drops of blood iſſuing from a wounded heart.</hi> Thus it is with the man now laboring in his <hi>new birth,</hi> his heart grieves, his eye weeps, whence the Proverb, <hi>The way to heaven is by weeping croſs;</hi> the way to Gods kingdom is to cry like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren coming into the world, the way to be <hi>new born</hi> is to feel throws (as a woman laboring of childe) and ſo is Chriſt formed in us. Can <hi>a man be born again</hi> without bitterneſs of ſoul? no, if ever he come to a ſight of ſin, and that Gods ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Spirit work in him <hi>ſorrow for ſin,</hi> his ſoul will mourn till he may ſay with <hi>Jeremy, Mine eye droppeth without ſtay — mine eye breaketh my heart, becauſe of all the daughters of my City,</hi> becauſe of all the ſins of my ſoul, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.51. True it is,
<note place="margin">Lam. 3.49, 51.</note> as ſome infants are born with more pain to the mother, and ſome with leſs, ſo may the <hi>new man</hi> be regenerated in ſome with more, in ſome with leſs anxiety of travel; but more or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30627:21"/>leſs, it cannot be ſo little, but the man that labors in theſe pangs ſhall mourn, and mourn, <hi>There ſhall be a great mourning, as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon,</hi> Zach. 12.11. What elſe?
<note place="margin">Zach. 12.11.</note> He cannot look on a Saint, that ſailed not firſt through the Ocean of tears, and therefore he falls on his face with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17.17. Gen. 32.24. Iob 3. 1 Sam. 1.15. Pſal. 119.136. Iſa. 38.14.</note> he wreſtles with God like <hi>Jacob,</hi> he roars out his grief with <hi>Job,</hi> he pours out his ſoul with <hi>Hanna,</hi> he weeps rivers of tears with <hi>David,</hi> he <hi>mourns as a dove</hi> with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> yea, <hi>like a crane, or a ſwallow, ſo doth he chatter,</hi> Iſa. 38.14. O the bitter pangs and ſore travel of <hi>a man,</hi> when he muſt <hi>be born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth ſtep is, <hi>Seeking rightly for comfort:</hi> He runs not to the world, or fleſh, or Divel, <hi>miſerable comforters all,</hi> but to Scripture, to Prayer, or to the Miniſtery of Gods word; if he finde comfort in Scriptures, he meets with it in the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lex oſtendit peccatum, at Solum Evangelium peccati remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Aug. tract.</hi> 17. <hi>in Joh.</hi>
                  </note> Goſpel; not the Law, but <hi>the Goſpel</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is the power of God to ſalvation, to every one that believeth,</hi> Rom. 1.16. The Law is indeed <hi>the miniſtery of death and damnation,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.7. but <hi>the Gospel is the glad tidings of ſalvation,</hi> Luk. 2.10. The Law ſhews a man his wretched eſtate, but ſhews him no remedy, and yet we aboliſh not the Law, in aſcribing this comfort to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel onely;
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16. 2 Cor. 3.7. Luk. 2.10.</note> though it be no cauſe of it, yet is it the occaſion of it: thoſe doleful terrors, and fears of conſcience begotten by the Law, may be in their own nature the very gates and downfal to the pit of hell; yet I cannot deny, but they are certain occaſions of receiving grace; and if it pleaſe God that the man, now labor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his pangs of <hi>the new birth,</hi> do but rightly ſettle his thoughts on the Goſpel of Chriſt, no doubt but thence he may ſuck the ſweeteſt comforts and delights that ever were revealed to man. Or if he finde comfort in prayer (to which he ever and anon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairs in every of theſe ſteps) then is it by Chriſt, in whoſe name onely he approacheth to that heavenly throne of grace: no ſooner had the King of <hi>Niniveh</hi> humbled himſelf, but his proclamation runs,
<note place="margin">Ionah 3.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Let man and beast be covered with ſack cloth, and cry mightily unto God, — Who can tell if God will turn and repent, and turn away from his fierce anger, that we periſh not?</hi> and thus the man now wreſtling with the grievous afflictions and terrors of his conſcience, <hi>Who can tell</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if God will turn away his fierce anger? let me then cry mightily unto the Lord of heaven,</hi> let
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30627:21"/>me cry, and continue crying, until the Lord of mercy do in mercy look upon me; and if for all this God give him a repulſe, for reaſons beſt known to himſelf, if at the firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, or at many more times, he ſeem to have cryed in vain, at laſt he flyes to the miniſtery of the Word, and if he may have his will, he would hit upon the moſt skilful, experienced, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſound-dealing man amongſt all Gods Meſſengers: thus was it with <hi>Peters</hi> hearers, whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> being <hi>pricked,</hi> and rent with legal terrors, then could they begin to cry it out, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall we do?</hi> Act. 2.37.
<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> Thus was it with the <hi>Jaylor,</hi> who after his <hi>trembling and falling down to the ground</hi> in an humble abaſement, could then begin to ſay, <hi>Sirs, what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> Act. 16.30.
<note place="margin">Act. 16.30.</note> And thus the man now ready to <hi>be born again,</hi> if he finde no means to aſſwage the rage and terrors of his guilty conſcience, at laſt he comes to Gods Miniſter with a <hi>What ſhall I do, what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> Alas! now I feel the wounded conſcience, the broken heart, the ſpiritual blindneſs, the captivity and poverty of which often you have told me; if then there be any inſtruction, direction or duty, which may tend to my good, or free me from this evil, now open thoſe <hi>lips that ſhould preſerve knowledge,</hi> now direct me in Gods fear, and I will willingly follow it with my utmoſt endeavors.</p>
               <p>And now (and not till now) hath Gods Miniſter a ſtrong and ſeaſonable calling to amplifie and magnifie the ſoul-ſaving ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of Chriſts death and paſſion; were the blood of Chriſt, and promiſe of Salvation proffered to an unwounded conſcience, what were it, but like the pouring of a moſt ſoveraign balſam upon a ſound member of man? It is the onely, right, everlaſting method, firſt to wound by the Law, and then to heal by the Goſpel; firſt to cauſe ſmart for ſin, and then to lay to a plaiſter of Chriſts blood; and therefore when the heart is broken, then hath the <hi>man of God</hi> his warrant to binde it up again, then may he magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods mercy, then may he ſet out to the height the heavenly beauty of Chriſts paſſion and perſon, and thus playing the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife by his high and holy art of comforting the afflicted, at laſt the childe of God (prepared for his birth) becomes a man <hi>born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifth ſtep is a clear (I ſay not a general ſight, which he had before) but <hi>The clear ſight of Chriſt laid open to the eye of Faith;</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:30627:22"/>no ſooner is the poor wounded ſoul informed throughly in the myſtery and mercy of the Goſpel, but he then looks on his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or as the Jews on the brazen ſerpent, and ſeeing him lifted up on the croſs, he cannot but ſee in him an infinite treaſury of mercy and love, a boundleſs and bottomleſs ſea of tender-heartedneſs and pity, a whole heaven of ſweetneſs, happineſs, peace and pleaſures; After the <hi>ſpirit of bondage,</hi> enters the <hi>Spirit of adoption;</hi> the terrors of the Law leads him to the comforts of the Goſpel, his ſorrow for ſin brings him to the clear light of his Savior; and then as a man in deaths-pangs, that lifts up his eyes to heaven <hi>whence cometh his help,</hi> ſo he in births-pangs lifts up his eyes to Chriſt, who muſt either help him, or he ſinks under his ſin to the bottomleſs bottom of hell. And I muſt tell you, this ſight of Chriſt Jeſus to an humbled ſinner (together with thoſe glorious priviledges which he brings with him, as Reconciliation to God, forgiveneſs of ſins, adoption, juſtification, righteouſneſs, wiſdom, ſanctification,
<note place="margin">Matth. 6.29.</note> redemption, it is a moſt pleaſant, raviſhing, heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſight: <hi>Not Solomon in all his royalty,</hi> no, <hi>nor the lillies of the field arrayed better then Solomon;</hi> not all the curious ſights on earth, nor all thoſe glittering ſpangles in heaven, can poſſibly afford ſuch pleaſure or delight to the eye of man, as doth this one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (Chriſt bleeding on the croſs) to the ſoul of a ſinner. Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that you ſaw ſome malefactor (whoſe tryal and doom were paſt) to be led to the doleful place of execution; imagine that you heard him wail and weep for his miſ-ſpent time, for his bloody acts, for his heynous crimes; yea imagine his wailings and weepings ſo bitter, that they were able to force tears from others, and to make all eyes ſhoot and water that but lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; if this man in this caſe ſhould ſuddenly ſee his King run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and riding towards him with his pardon in his hand, what a ſight would this be? ſure there is none to this. Thus, thus it is with the man ſorrowing for ſin, whileſt he is weeping his caſe, and confeſſing what a little ſtep there is betwixt him and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (as if he were now at hells mouth, the very place of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution) in a maze he looks upon Chriſt, whom he ſees with a ſpear in his ſide, with thorns in his head, with nails in his feet, with a pardon in his hands, offering it to all men that will but receive it by faith. O here's a ſight indeed, able to revive the wickedſt man upon earth, dead in ſins and treſpaſſes. And now
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30627:22"/>there is hopes of the <hi>birth,</hi> if it once come to this, there is more then probability of an happy delivery, we may call it the ſtirrings of Gods childe, or the firſt feelings of life, before he is <hi>born again.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The ſixth ſtep is, <hi>An hungring deſire after Chriſt and his merits,</hi> and to this ſtep bleſſed are they that arrive; <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs, for they ſhall be filled,</hi> Matth.
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.6.</note> 5.6. Filled? how? <hi>I will give unto him that is athirſt, of the fountain of the water of life freely,</hi> Revel. 21.6.
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.6.</note> this is the ſtep (as if it were in <hi>Jacobs ladder</hi>) that raiſeth him on high to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven; it is ſuch a token of true faith, that he who hath it, needs no more doubt that he believeth, then he that breatheth needs to doubt that he liveth; and why? his thirſt of worldly things is cooled, his thirſt of heavenly things inflamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that drinks of the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sol. <hi>Non ſiti miſerae indigentiae, ſed ſiti copioſioris fruitionis.</hi> No hungry man did ever with more appetite wiſh for meat, nor thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty man for drink, nor covetous man for money, nor ambitious man for glory, then he now longeth to be reconciled unto God in Chriſt; in this caſe, had he the pleaſures and profits of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds, willingly would he part with all for the application of Chriſts ſufferings, it is that ſoveraign blood that can onely heal his ſoul, it is that bitter paſſion which can onely quench his thirſt; give him but the merits of Chriſts death (whereby God and he may be at one) and he cares not though he ſuffer death and hell again, yea he will venture goods, life, all; or if that be not it which the Lord requires, he will do whatever behoves him, even <hi>ſell all, all that he hath,</hi> part with all ſin that he loveth, yea were it <hi>his right hand,</hi> or <hi>his right eye,</hi> nothing ſhall be dear to him, ſo that he may injoy his Savior. O here's a thirſt above all thirſts! it breeds ardent deſires, vehement longings, unutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able groans, mighty gaſpings, juſt like the dry and thirſty ground, that gaſps, and cleaves, and opens for drops of rain. <hi>David,</hi> though in the deſert of <hi>Ziph, a barren and dry land without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> yet he complains moſt becauſe of his thirſt, <hi>My ſoul thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for thee O God,</hi> Pſal. 63.1.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.1.</note> This is that violent affection that God puts into the hearts of thoſe who ſeek him in ſincerity and truth; never was <hi>Ahab</hi> more ſick for a vineyard, nor <hi>Siſera</hi> for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30627:23"/>milk, nor <hi>Sampſon</hi> for water, when God was fain to open him a fountain in <hi>the jaw of an aſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 15 19.</note> then is a truly humbled ſoul af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, ever thirſting and longing, that he may hide himſelf in his righteouſneſs, and bathe himſelf in that blood which his Savior ſhed for him. I have read of a gracious woman, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring in theſe pangs, and longing after Chriſt Jeſus, cryed out, <hi>I have born nine children with as great pain as other women, and yet I would with all my heart bear them all over again, yea bear them, and bear them all the days of my life, to be aſſured of my part in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> One replying; Doth not your heart deſire and long after him? <hi>Oh!</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I have an husband and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and many other comforts, I would give them all, and all the good I ſhall ever ſee in this world, or in in the world to come, to have my poor thirſty ſoul refreſht with that precious blood of my Savior.</hi> So eager and earneſt is the heart of each man (parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the angry countenance of God) after this blood of his; I thirſt, I faint, I languiſh, I long (ſaith he) for one drop of mercy; my ſpirit is melted in me into tears of blood; my heart, becauſe of ſin, is ſo ſhaken and ſhivered; my ſoul, becauſe of ſorrow, is ſo waſted and parched, that my thirſt is inſatiable, my bowels are hot within me, my deſire after Chriſt is extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great and greedy. Stay! all theſe expreſſions are far ſhort of thoſe longings,
<note place="margin">Rev. 2 17.</note> 
                  <hi>no man knoweth them, ſave he that receives them,</hi> ſave he that is <hi>born again.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The ſeventh ſtep is, <hi>A relying on Chriſt:</hi> no ſooner he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and remembers thoſe many melting invitations of our Lord and Savior:
<note place="margin">Iohn 7.31. Iſaiah 55.1. Matth. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come unto me: Ho, every one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters: Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden</hi> with ſin: but (reſting himſelf on the impregnable truth of theſe bleſſed promiſes) he throws himſelf into the merciful and meritorious arms of his crucified Lord. Come life, come death, come heaven, come hell, come what come will,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35, 38, 39.</note> here will he ſtick for ever: <hi>Who</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>ſhall ſeperate us from the love of Chriſt? Shall tribulation, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſs, or peril, or ſword?</hi> No: <hi>I am perſwaded</hi> (not theſe, nor more then theſe) <hi>neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeperate us from the love of God, which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30627:23"/>is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> Rom. 8.35, 38, 39. Thus it is with the man laboring in this <hi>birth:</hi> what (ſaith he) doth Chriſt call the heavy laden? why, Lord, I am heavy laden with a weight, a maſs of ſin, and if he may come that is called, Lord, I come, I come, and now I am come, with thee will I build <hi>my tabernacle,</hi> with thee will I reſt for ever. Nor is this any wonder, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells us, the hunted beaſt flyes unto his den, the wounded man hyes unto the Surgeon, and ſo the poor man broken and bruiſed with the weight of ſin, how ſhould he otherwiſe but caſt himſelf willingly into the ſweet compaſſionate inviting armes and embracements of Chriſt, whoſe promiſes run, <hi>I will eaſe him, I will refreſh him?</hi> You may ſee ſometimes a little infant,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28.</note> upon apprehenſion and approach of ſome ſudden danger, how haſtily he runs into his mothers arms: even ſo a truly wounded ſoul (purſued by the terrors of the Law, and frighted with the angry countenance of Almighty God) it flyes with ſpeed into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of its bleſſed Redeemer, there it clings unto his bleſſed wounds, there it reſts upon his meritorious death, there it graſps about his crucified body, there it hides it ſelf in the clefts of this Rock, yea there it ſticks with this full reſolution, that ſhould all terrors, all temptations, all men, all devils, combine together to caſt him into hell, they ſhould tear him, rent him, pull him, hale him from the bleeding wounds, and tender bowels of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Savior. This was <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe, who in the bittereſt of his pangs could cry it out, ſaying, <hi>Though the Lord ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him,</hi> Job 13.15. And I muſt tell you, <hi>this</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vriſin. parte ſecunda catech. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>Fides juſtificans non eſt tantum noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſed etiam fiducia, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanquam medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um applicamus nobis meritum Chriſti, ac in eo acquieſcimus.</hi> Trelcat. l. 2. inſtitut. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens de natura fidei juſtifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, apprehenſio ejus</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ex</hi> 
                     <hi>una cognitionis in intellectu, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera fiduciae in voluntate, utram<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit fides— At noluit Bellar. fidem eſſe in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>affiance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, adherence, reliance</hi> (or whatſoever elſe we call it) <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the merits of Chriſt, is the right juſtifying faith,</hi> whither if a man once come, there is but one degree more, and he is then <hi>born again.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The laſt and higheſt ſtep is, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal obedience to Chriſt.</hi> No ſooner hath he caſt himſelf upon him, but he takes him (not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a Savior to redeem him from the miſeries of ſin, but) as an husband, a Lord, a King, to ſerve him, love him, honor him, and obey him: Now will he <hi>take his yoke upon him;</hi> now will he <hi>bear his croſs and follow after him;</hi> now will he <hi>enter into the narrow way;</hi> now will he <hi>walk in the holy path;</hi> now will he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate himſelf to that <hi>ſect and brotherhood that is every where ſpoken againſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 28.22.</note> now will he oppoſe himſelf againſt all ſin what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30627:24"/>now will he ſhake off his old companions, <hi>brethren in iniquity;</hi> now will he keep peace and a good conſcience towards God and man; now will he watch over his ſecret ſins, luſtful thoughts, occaſions of evil; now will he direct his words to the glorifying of God, and to give grace to the hearers; now will he conform all his actions to the ſoveraignty of grace; now will he delight in the word, the ways, the Saints, the ſervices of God; now will he never more turn again unto folly, or to his trade of ſin, yea though Satan ſet upon him with baits and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, to detain him in his bondage, but by one darling-delight, one minion-ſin, yet he reſolves to anſwer him as <hi>Moſes</hi> did <hi>Pharaoh, There ſhall not ſo much as an hoof be left behinde;</hi> for well he knows, one breach in the City expoſeth it to the enemy, one leak in a ſhip will ſink it in the ſea, one ſtab in the heart will ſpeed a man to death, one knot in a threed will ſtay the needles paſſage as well as five hundred, and therefore he will <hi>ſell all, all that he hath,</hi> even all his ſins, to the laſt filthy rag of his minion-delight, his bewitching-beloved-boſom-ſin. And now is <hi>the new man born</hi> amongſt us, will you view him? <hi>Old things are paſſed away,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>behold, all things are become new,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.17. His heart, his eye, his ear, his tongue, his underſtanding, his will, his memory, his conſcience; his love, his hatred, his hope, his fear, his joy, his ſorrow; will you any more? his thoughts, his words, his actions, his affections, are all <hi>new;</hi> this converſion is univerſal, this change is a through change; now is Chriſt form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, now is he transformed into a <hi>new creature,</hi> before he was in making a new man, but now he is made <hi>new,</hi> God the Father accepts him for his ſon, God the Son ſtamps on him the Image of his Father, but more immediately God the Holy Ghoſt hath thus moulded and faſhioned him, as I have let you ſee him, and now he is <hi>born again</hi>] which <hi>except a man be,—he</hi> (ſhall not) <hi>cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Lo here thoſe ſteps that raiſe up a man to the ſtate of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>A ſight of ſin, Senſe of miſery, Sorrow for ſin, Seeking for comfort, A ſight of Chriſt, Deſire after Chriſt, Relying on Chriſt, Obedience to Chriſt:</hi> one word more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have done.</q>
               <p>You ſee how God brings along the man whom he purpoſeth to make his; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> and yet let no truly humbled ſinner be diſcouraged
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30627:24"/>if he obſerve not ſo diſtinctly the order of theſe ſteps, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in that degree as (you ſee) we have related; for if in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and effect they have been wrought in them, if he have them in truth (though perhaps not in this degree) I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce of him, that he is ſurely <hi>born again.</hi> It is one of our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies hath ſaid it, that <hi>in our humiliations, and other preparative diſpoſitions, we do not preſcribe preciſely juſt ſuch a meaſure and quantity, we do not determine peremptorily upon ſuch or ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and height, we leave that to the wiſdom of our great Maſter in heaven, the onely wiſe God, who is a moſt free agent: But ſure we are, a man muſt have ſo much, and in that meaſure, as throughly to humble him, and then to bring him to his Savior; he muſt be weary of all his ſins, and of Satans bondage wholly, willing to pluck out his right eye, and cut off his right hand, I mean to part with his beſt-beloved boſom lusts, to ſell all, and not to leave ſo much as an hoof behinde; he muſt ſee his danger, and ſo haſte to the City of refuge; he muſt be ſenſible of his ſpiritual miſery, that he may heartily thirſt for mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y; he muſt finde himſelf loſt and caſt away in himſelf, that Chriſt may be all in all unto him; and after muſt follow an hatred of all falſe and evil ways for the time to come, a through-change of former courſes, company, converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſetting himſelf in the way and practice of ſobriety, honeſty, and holineſs.</hi> The ſum is, of every ſoul is required thus much: firſt, a truly penitent ſight, ſenſe, and hatred of all ſin: ſecondly, a ſincere and unſatiable thirſt after Jeſus Chriſt, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both imputed and inherent: thirdly, an unfained, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſerved reſolution of an univerſal <hi>new obedience</hi> for the time to come. If any man hath had the experience of theſe affections and effects in his own ſoul, whatſoever the meaſure be (leſs or more) he is ſafe enough, and may go on comfortably in the holy path.</p>
               <p>Now then let me adviſe thee (whomſoever thou art that readeſt) to enter into thine own ſoul, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> and examine thine own ſtate, whether or no thou art yet <hi>born again:</hi> Search and ſee, whether as yet the <hi>ſpirit of bondage</hi> hath wrought its effects in thee; that is to ſay, whether thou haſt been illightened, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, and terrified with a ſenſible apprehenſion, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar acknowledgement of thy wretched eſtate: Search and ſee, whether as yet <hi>the Spirit of adoption</hi> hath ſealed thee for his own; that is to ſay, Whether (after thy heart being broken,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30627:25"/>thy ſpirit bruiſed, thy ſoul humbled, thy conſcience wounded and awaked) thou haſt had a ſight of Chriſt, and haſt thirſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, and haſt caſt thy ſelf on him, and haſt followed his ways and Commandments by an univerſal obedience? If upon ſearch thou canſt ſay (without ſelf-deceit) that ſo it is with thee, then mayeſt thou bleſs God that ever thou waſt born, certainly (I dare ſay it) thou art <hi>born again.</hi> But if thou haſt not ſenſe or feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe works, if all I have ſpoken are very myſteries to thee, what ſhall I ſay? but if ever, if ever thou meaneſt to <hi>ſee the kingdom of God, ſtrive, ſtruggle, endeavor with thy might and main</hi> to become truly regenerate: thus whileſt the Miniſter ſpeaks, it is Chriſt that comes with power in the word, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31, 32. thou mayeſt ſay perhaps, it is not in thy power, thou art onely a meer patient, and Gods Spirit the agent, and who can command the ſpirit of the Lord, that <hi>bloweth where he liſteth,</hi> at his own will and pleaſure? I anſwer, It is indeed the Spirit, and not man, that regenerates or ſanctifies: but I anſwer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, The doctrine of the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l is the miniſtration of the Spirit, and whereſoever that is preached (as I preach it now to thee) there is the holy Ghoſt preſent, and thither he comes to regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: nay, I can ſay more, there is a common work of illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that makes way for regeneration; and this common work puts a power into man of doing that, which when he ſhall do, the Spirit of God may, nay will in the day of his power mightily work in him, to his quickening and purging; if then as yet thou feeleſt not this mighty work of God in thee, and yet fain wouldſt feel it, and gladly doſt deſire it (otherwiſe I confeſs it is in vain to ſpeak) follow me in theſe paſſages; I ſhall lend thee two wings to bear thee, two hands to lead thee to the foot of this ladder, where if thou aſcend theſe ſteps aforeſaid, I dare certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pronounce of thee, thou art the <hi>man born again.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The firſt wing is <hi>Prayer,</hi> which firſt brings thee to Gods throne, and (there, if thou haſt thy requeſt) then to <hi>the new birth;</hi> if I muſt acquaint thee how to pray; <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. <hi>Take with you words, and turn to the Lord; ſay unto him, take away all iniquity, and receive us graciouſly,</hi>—and then it follows, <hi>I will heal their backſliding, I will love them freely,</hi> ver. 4. Jerem. 30.18. <hi>I have ſurely heard</hi> Ephraim <hi>bemoaning himſelf thus, Thou haſt chaſtiſed me, and I was chaſtiſed, as a bullock unaccuſtomed to the yoak, turn
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30627:25"/>thou me, and I ſhall be turned.</hi> The ſoul may object, <hi>I may ſay thus, and be no better:</hi> But I anſwer, ſay it, though you be no better, becauſe God bids you ſay it: Say it, and ſay it again; it may be he will come in when you ſay it, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.4. Pray that God would pleaſe to prepare thy heart, to ſanctifie thy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to order thy will, to preſerve thee from ſin, to prepare thee for growth unto full holineſs and righteouſneſs: this was the effect of <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> prayer, <hi>Convert me, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 31.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and I ſhall be converted; heal me, O Lord, and I ſhall be healed; ſave me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 17.14.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, and I ſhall be ſaved: Turn thou us, O good Lord, and ſo ſhall we be turned,</hi> Jer. 17.14. and <hi>Lament.</hi> 5.21.
<note place="margin">Lam. 5.21.</note> It is the Lord that converts, and heals, and ſaves, and turns; and <hi>Prayer is the means to produce this effect in thee:</hi> when we are required to pray, to repent, and believe, we are not to ſeek ſtrength in our ſelves, but to ſearch into the Covenant, and turn the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe into prayer. As the Command is, <hi>Repent, Act.</hi> 17.30. Now the Covenant is, <hi>Chriſt ſhall give repentance,</hi> Act. 5.31. and therefore pray, <hi>Turn thou me, and I ſhall be turned, Jer.</hi> 31.18. then bow thy knees, and humbly, heartily, frequently, fervently implore the influence of Gods bleſſed ſpirit: Cry with the Spouſe in the Canticles, <hi>Awake, O North-wind,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and come thou South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, and blow upon my garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow forth,</hi> Cantic. 4.16. The more ruſhing and mighty this <hi>wind of the Spirit</hi> is, the more will he make thee fructifie in his graces and bleſſings; therefore cry again and again, <hi>O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.10.</note> 
                  <hi>let thy Spirit come upon me: create in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me. O Lord Jeſu, ſend thy Spirit into me, which may reſtore me from this death of ſin, unto the life of holineſs.</hi> Thus wouldeſt thou ask, and continue asking; thus wouldeſt thou cry, and continue crying, then could I aſſure thee of the promiſe which God hath made, and cannot deny, <hi>he that asketh receiveth;</hi> and, <hi>he that ſeeketh findeth;</hi> and,
<note place="margin">Matth 7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>to him that knocketh</hi> (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and perſeverance) <hi>it ſhall be opened,</hi> Mat. 7.8.</p>
               <p>The ſecond wing, or hand, that bears and leads thee to theſe ſteps of <hi>the new birth,</hi> is, <hi>Conſtant hearing of the Word:</hi> thou muſt attend <hi>the gates of wiſdom, and wait on her poſts;</hi> thou muſt come to Gods houſe, and hearken to the miniſtery of the Word: <hi>no doubt, but if thou beeſt conſtant in this duty, God will ſtir up ſome good</hi> Samuel, <hi>God will uſe ſome of his Prieſts (conſecrated to that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30627:26"/>office) to beget thee again:</hi> Underſtand this ſoberly; for if Jeſus Chriſt himſelf ſhould preach to the ſoul every day, and give not out of himſelf, the ordinance would be empty to it: it is Chriſts coming in to his people in the ordinances, that onely fills the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty ſoul with good things. To this purpoſe are Gods Miniſters called Spiritual Fathers, <hi>I have begotten you</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>through the miniſtration of the Goſpel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.15.</note> 1 Cor. 4.15. The Paſtors tongue is the Lords Conduit-pipe, and hereby he drives the ſweet and wholſom waters of life into the ſouls of his choſen; onely do thou frequent the means, and thou ſhalt ſee at one time or other, God will remember thee in mercy: It is true, I know not when; and therefore I wiſh thee miſs no Lords-day to repair to Gods houſe, leſt the day of thy neglect might have been the day of thy converſion; certain it is, no man ſhould expect Gods bleſſing without his ordinances; no eating of bread without plowing and ſowing, no recovering of health without eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking, no poſting on land without ſomewhat to ride on, no paſſage on ſeas, without ſomewhat to ſail in; ſo no bleſſing, no grace, no regeneration, no <hi>new birth</hi> at all, without waiting upon God in his ways, and in his ordinances. Now then, as thou deſireſt heaven, or (the way to heaven) to <hi>be born again, I beſeech thee make high account of this ordinance of God, the preaching of his Word:</hi> In preaching of the Goſpel, light, moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and power goes out to all, which men reſiſt: and ſome are deſtroyed, not becauſe they could not believe, but becauſe they reſiſt, and will not obey, and ſo dye, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.34. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9. and yet I wiſh thee not onely to hear it, but after thou haſt heard, conſider of it, ponder on it, and lay the threats and reproofs, the precepts and promiſes, unto thine own ſoul: thus if thou heareſt and meditateſt, I doubt not but Gods word will be a <hi>Word of power</hi> to thee, and (together with <hi>prayer</hi>) bring thee towards <hi>the new birth,</hi> whither <hi>except a man</hi> come, <hi>he cannot</hi> (poſſibly) <hi>ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far of <hi>the new birth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> you ſee we have mounted thoſe ſteps, whoſe <hi>top</hi> (like <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder) <hi>reacheth up to heaven;</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the next word, he that is <hi>born again</hi> ſhall <hi>ſee the kingdom of God,</hi> but he that is not <hi>born again, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>He cannot ſee the kingdom of God.]</head>
               <p>THe priviledges of <hi>the new birth</hi> are theſe two, <hi>to ſee,</hi>] and <hi>to ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>]</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:30627:26"/>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>to ſee,</hi>] Which is all one (ſaith a Modern) as to <hi>enjoy:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aretius in loc.</note> yet a man may ſee that which he doth not enjoy; but without regeneration there is no ſight, much leſs poſſeſſion of <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To <hi>ſee</hi> then is the leſſer happineſs, of which the unregenerate are debarred; but to <hi>ſee,</hi> in it ſelf is a great and gracious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to which the regenerate are admitted: for whether by <hi>Gods kingdom</hi> be meant the kingdom of grace, or the kingdom of glory, <hi>Happy are the eyes that ſee theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whoſe <hi>eyes</hi> are they? If we examine the unregenerate, he ſees no whit into the awful Majeſty of God the Father, he ſees no whit of the beauty, mercy, and pity of his Savior, he ſees no whit into that glorious highneſs of Gods Spirit in Heaven, nor yet of his nighneſs to his brethren on earth: Hence it is, that when he comes into the Temple, among the Congregation of Gods Saints, his ſoul is not delighted with their prayers, praiſes, Pſalms, and Service; he <hi>ſees</hi> no comfort, no pleaſure, no content in their actions. But the <hi>new man</hi> is of better <hi>ſight,</hi> the graces of the Spirit, and the ward-robe of Gods glory are all produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to his eye, as if the Lord ſhould ſay, <hi>Come, and ſee:</hi> ſo <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Stand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Venite, &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dete.</hi> Pſal. 46.8. Exod. 14.13. Epheſ. 1.18. Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 3.18.</note> ſo Chriſt to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>It is given to your eyes to ſee theſe things, to others but by parables.</hi> He that is <hi>born again</hi> hath a ſpiritual eye, and a cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial object, <hi>The eye of his underſtanding is enlightned</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul:) anointed</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>John:</hi>) To what end? But that he may <hi>know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance is in the Saints,</hi> Epheſ. 1.18. See a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of which the unregenerate is ever barred, his minde is dark, even <hi>darkneſs</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. And therefore it is no wonder,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.8.</note> what is ſaid by our Savior, that <hi>he cannot, cannot ſee</hi>] <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond priviledge is the object of this ſight, here called <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi>] By which ſome underſtand Heaven, ſome the way to Heaven; moſt of the Ancients ſay, that by this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is meant Heaven: <hi>Calvin</hi> is of minde, that <hi>not heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calvin in loc Aretius in loc. Parum refert.</note> 
                  <hi>but a spiritual life is thereby underſtood: Aretius</hi> ſaith (and I am of his minde) that whether we underſtand the one or the other, <hi>It matters not much:</hi> Sure we are, that both theſe (<hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi>) are annexed to <hi>the new birth,</hi> and both very well
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30627:27"/>may be implyed in this word, <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Firſt then, if by <hi>the kingdom of God</hi> is meant the kingdom of Grace (whereof our Savior ſpeaketh, <hi>The kingdom of God is within you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 17.21.</note> Luke 17.21.) See to what a priviledge the <hi>new man</hi> hath attained, all the graces of God, all the fruits of the Spirit are now poured into him: If you ask what graces? what fruits? St.
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> tells you, Gal. 5.22. <hi>Love, joy, peace, long-ſufferings, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance:</hi> or would you have us to contract them? St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth it elſewhere, <hi>the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is—righteouſneſs, peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom.
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> 14.17.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that is either <hi>active</hi> or <hi>paſſive;</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of life, or (the cauſe of this holineſs) our <hi>righteouſneſs in Chriſt:</hi> If the firſt be meant, no ſooner is <hi>man born again,</hi> but he enters into <hi>the holy path,</hi> he declines all evil, and ſtands at the ſword point with his moſt beloved ſin; or if ever any ſin (through the violence of temptation) ſeize on him again, he is preſently put again into the pangs of <hi>the new birth,</hi> and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing his ſorrow, and repairing repentance, he becomes more reſolute and watchful over all his ways:
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.9.</note> And as he <hi>abhors evil,</hi> ſo <hi>he cleaves to that which is good;</hi> his <hi>faith</hi> like the <hi>Sun,</hi> ſets all thoſe gracious heavenly ſtars on ſhining, as <hi>hope, and love, and zeal, and humility, and patience;</hi> in a word, <hi>univerſal obedience, and fruitfulneſs in all good works:</hi> not one, but all good duties of the firſt and ſecond Table, begin to be natural and familiar to him, and though he finde ſome duties more difficult, yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth, and ſtriveth to do what he can, and is much diſpleaſed and grieved, if he do not as he ſhould. Or if by <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> is meant <hi>paſſive righteouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30.</note> to wit, <hi>our righteouſneſs in Chriſt,</hi> no ſooner is <hi>a man born again,</hi> but he is cloathed with this <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> the other (God knows) is but weak and full of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection,
<note place="margin">Extra nos eſt juſtitia, non in nobis: Luther. de inſtit. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana.</note> and therefore to ſpeak properly, <hi>It is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in God, that makes us appear righteous afore God:</hi> would you have a plain caſe? as <hi>Jacob</hi> to procure the bleſſing of his father, hid himſelf into the apparel of his brother, and ſo received it to his own commodity, under the perſon of another: thus the <hi>new man</hi> puts on the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, with which being clad as with a garment, God accepts him in his ſtead, his faults being covered with his Saviors perfection.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:30627:27"/>
               <p>Secondly, from this <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ariſeth <hi>Peace:</hi> no ſooner is man righteous, but he is at <hi>peace</hi> with man, at <hi>peace</hi> with God, at <hi>peace</hi> with himſelf. He is at <hi>peace with man;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.6.</note> 
                  <hi>The wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard with the Kid,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.6. The meaning is, that in the kingdom of Chriſt, when a man is called into the ſtate of grace (howſoever by nature he is a <hi>Wolf,</hi> or a <hi>Leopard,</hi> or a <hi>Lyon,</hi> or a <hi>Bear,</hi> yet) he ſhall then lay aſide his cruelty, and live peaceably with all men, with <hi>all men,</hi> I ſay, <hi>bad and good;</hi> for if <hi>bad,</hi> the Apoſtle implyes them, <hi>As much as in you is, have peace with all men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.18.</note> Rom. 12.18. Or if <hi>good,</hi> then he cannot but have <hi>peace</hi> with them, yea, although before his converſion he hated and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligned them, yet now he is raviſhed with the delight and love of them, and to this end he labors might and main to ingratiate himſelf into their bleſſed Communion; true, how ſhould he but love them, and ſympathize with them, whom he believes one day to meet in Heaven, and there to enjoy them, and they him for ever? Nor is this all, he is at <hi>peace with God,</hi> he hath hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf, and confeſt his fault, and cryed for <hi>mercy,</hi> and caſt himſelf upon Chriſt, and vowed amendment of life; ſo that now God by his word hath ſpoke <hi>peace</hi> to his ſoul, by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Chriſt it is obtained, and by the teſtimony of the Spirit he feels it within him. This is that <hi>Peace which paſſeth all underſtanding,</hi> it made the Angels ſing; <hi>Peace upon earth,</hi> it makes his ſoul reply, <hi>My peace is in heaven:</hi> what elſe? The ſtorm is paſt, and <hi>the rain is gone away,</hi> he that lay for a night in the darkneſs of ſorrow, and weeping for his ſins, now he beholds <hi>the Son of righteouſneſs appear</hi> (as the Diſciples often did upon the Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> ſignifying peace) all quiet, and calm, and pleaſant. Nor is this all, he is at <hi>peace with himſelf,</hi> I mean his own conſcience; that which before ſtirred up the fire, that brought him to a ſight of ſin, and ſenſe of Divine Wrath, that filled him with fearful terrors, compunction, remorſe, and true ſorrow for ſin, it is now turned good and quiet. <hi>Solomon</hi> calls it <hi>a continual feaſt,</hi> Prov. 15.15.
<note place="margin">Prov. 15.15.</note> who are the attendants but the holy Angels? what is the chear, but <hi>joy in the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> who is the feaſt-maker but God himſelf, and his good Spirit dwelling in him? Nor is this feaſt without muſick, Gods word and his actions make a bleſſed harmony, and he endeavors to continue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30627:28"/>it by keeping <hi>peace</hi> and a good conſcience towards God and man.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from this <hi>peace</hi> iſſueth <hi>joy in the holy Ghoſt;</hi> no ſooner is a man at <hi>peace</hi> with man, with God, with himſelf, but he is filled with <hi>joy</hi> that no man can take from him; this <hi>joy</hi> I take to be thoſe bleſſed ſtirrings of the heart, when the ſeal of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins is firſt ſet unto the ſoul by <hi>the spirit of Adoption;</hi> For thus it is, the ſoul having newly paſſed the pangs of <hi>the new birth,</hi> it is preſently bath'd in the blood of Chriſt, lull'd in the boſom of Gods mercies, ſecured by the Spirit of its inheritance above; and ſo ordinarily follows a Sea of comfort, a ſenſible taſte of everlaſting pleaſures, as if the man had already one foot in heaven. But I hear ſome object, They have felt the pangs, caſt themſelves on Chriſt, reſolved againſt all ſin, and yet no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort comes. It may be ſo, though not ordinarily; certain it is, whoſoever hath this <hi>joy</hi> is <hi>new born,</hi> yet not every one <hi>new born</hi> hath this <hi>joy;</hi> if any then be in ſuch caſe, let him hear what the Spirit of truth ſaith, <hi>Since the beginning of the world men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye ſeen, O God, beſides thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him,</hi> Iſaiah 64.4.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Waiting patiently</hi> (ſaith a Modern) <hi>for the Lords coming to comfort us, either in temporal or spiritual diſtreſſes, is a right pleaſing and acceptable duty and ſervice unto God, which he is wont to crown with multiplyed and overflowing refreſhings when he comes.</hi> To this end ſaith the Prophet, <hi>They that wait upon the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, and they ſhall walk and not faint,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.31.</note> Iſa. 40.31. Nay, and ſhould a man <hi>dye</hi> (ſaith my Author) <hi>in this ſtate of waiting, if his heart in the mean time ſincerely hate all ſin, heartily thirſt for the mercy of God in Chriſt, and reſolve truly upon new univerſal obedience for the time to come, he ſhall certainly be ſaved; becauſe the holy Ghoſt ſaith, Bleſſed are all they that wait for him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.18.</note> Iſa. 30.18. Or if this will not ſatisfie his <hi>deſire,</hi> let his <hi>deſire</hi> quicken and ſet on work (with extraordinary fervency) the ſpirit of <hi>prayer,</hi> let him have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe again and again unto the promiſes of Scripture towards the poor, heavy-laden, penitent ſouls; and when the time is come (if it will come) which God hath appointed, then ſhall he feel this joy unſpeakable, <hi>the joy of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30627:28"/>is the head, the height, the top, the higheſt ſtep in this kingdom of grace, <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or ſecondly, if by <hi>the kingdom of God</hi> is meant the <hi>kingdom of glory,</hi> ſee then what a priviledge waits on the <hi>new man;</hi> no ſooner ſhall his breath and body be divorced, but his ſoul mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the wings of Angels, ſhall ſtraight be carried above the ſtarry firmament, there ſhall it inherit <hi>the kingdom,</hi> Luke 12.32.
<note place="margin">Luke 12.32. Matth. 7.21. Acts 14.22.</note> an <hi>heavenly kingdom,</hi> Matth. 7.21. <hi>the kingdom of God,</hi> Act. 14.22. and truly called ſo, for 'tis a kingdom of Gods own making, beautifying and bleſſing; a kingdom beſeeming the glorious reſidence of the King of kings; a kingdom creating all Kings that but inhabit in it. But here my diſcourſe muſt give way to your meditations: I cannot ſpeak this priviledge, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude with <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> 
                  <hi>Anima quae amat aſcendat frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; currat per plateas caeleſtis Jeruſalem, viſitando Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas, ſalutando Prophetas, admirando exercitus. Mount your meditations on the wings of faith, and behold in Heaven thoſe ſtates of wonder, Patriarchs ſhining, Prophets praiſing, Saints admiring, hands clapping, harps warbling, hearts dancing, the exerciſe a ſong, the ditty Alleluiah, the quiriſters Saints, the conſorts An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">See more of this in my <hi>laſt things.</hi>
                  </note> In this fountain of pleaſure let the <hi>new-born Chriſtian</hi> bathe his ſoul, for his it is, and he it is onely that ſhall <hi>ſee</hi> it, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it; <hi>Except the man born again,</hi> no man ſhall ever <hi>ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Thus far of the priviledges of <hi>the new birth;</hi> there waits on it the <hi>eye of faith,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>joy in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> in a word, <hi>the kingdom of grace, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of glory.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And now (beloved) ſay, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> what would you do to obtain theſe priviledges? ſhould any hand reach you a Crown for the pains to take it? ſhould any but caſt at your feet a bag of gold, and you might make it your own for the ſtooping, would you not for ſo great a reward do ſo little a ſervice?
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.30.</note> and what is <hi>Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> but <hi>perfect freedom, the yoke is eaſie, the burthen is light,</hi> but the reward is grace, glory, endleſs felicity. <hi>Beſtir then your ſelves,</hi> and if ever you mean to <hi>ſee the kingdom of God, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to run through this new birth,</hi> and to lead a better life then
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30627:29"/>heretofore you have done. Thus whileſt the Miniſter ſpeaks, Chriſt comes with power, and therefore he ſpeaks and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades. I conclude with my ſpeeth to thee (whoſoever thou art) into whoſe hands this Book is fallen: the truth is, the work is weak, and anſwerable in that kinde to the Author of it: many and many a ſtitch in my ſide, many a pull at my heart, many a gripe in my ſtomack (beſides the pangs of my ſoul endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring to practice what I have writ) have I ſuffered and felt ſince I firſt begun it; and yet the comfort I have received my ſelf in this <hi>one neceſſary thing,</hi> hath made me (contrary to the deſires of my beſt friends) to run through this ſhort work, by taking a longer time, as my continual diſeaſe would now and then ſuffer me. If (when I am gone) thou reapeſt any ſpiritual good by this my ſurviving pains, it is, next to Gods glory, all my deſire; Yet I live, but to ſave thy ſoul I care not how ſoon I might dye, yea on that condition I could be willing (if God ſo pleaſed) the lines that thou readeſt were writ with the warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt blood in my heart: willing, ſaid I? yea, I could be willing and glad (as little blood as I have in my body) to let it run and run, for thy ſpiritual good, to the very laſt drop in my veins. I ſay no more, conſider what I have ſaid, <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:30627:29"/>
            <head>An appendix, containing a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Method, for the man not yet born again, to have his part in the ſecond birth.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The occaſion and method of this Treatiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome there are, who hearing <hi>the new birth</hi> (or firſt repentance) to be ſo neceſſary to ſalvation, but never feeling in themſelves any ſuch change or converſion, have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>deſired further helps,</hi> though naturally thou art blinde, and wretched, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and poor, and naked; yet the Lord hath not left thee without means and helps: to this purpoſe he hath ſet up his ordinances; not that man of himſelf can diſpoſe himſelf unto grace, but that the Spirit of Chriſt in the uſe of the ordinances (without any habitual or ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying grace in mans heart) can diſpoſe of man to the recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of habitual or ſanctifying grace. True it is, I adviſed them in the former Treatiſe to be <hi>frequent in prayer, and in hearing of the word:</hi> But ſo we have done, ſay they, and yet we feel no conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: it may be ſo, for not always the doing of them, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in them through Chriſt obtains the bleſſing deſired. And yet if they will out of hand <hi>ſettle themſelves to the work,</hi> It is the Lord that ſaith, <hi>Break up the fallow ground,</hi> Jer. 4.3. <hi>(i.)</hi> ſeek to the Lord to break them for thee: Be in the uſe of the means, and the Lord may come in, and break thy heart. I ſhall, for their further ſatisfaction, give them a more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Method,</hi> and without a Text taken, take my ſelf more liberty to put them in the way.</p>
               <p>Two things I ſuppoſe neceſſary for them that would have part in the <hi>new birth,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:30627:30"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To get into it.</item>
                     <item>2. To be delivered of it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The means to get into it, is
<list>
                           <item>1. Examination of themſelves.</item>
                           <item>2. Confeſſion of their ſins.</item>
                           <item>3. Hearty prayer for the ſoftning of their hearts.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>By which three are procured the three firſt ſteps,
<list>
                           <item>Sight of ſin.</item>
                           <item>Senſe of divine wrath.</item>
                           <item>Sorrow for ſin.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The means to be delivered of it, is by application of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and theſe, according to their ſeveral objects, produce their ſeveral effects; ſome
<list>
                           <item>A ſight of Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>A deſire after Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>A relying on Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>An obedience to Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>A comfort in Chriſt, not onely ſought for, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, if the promiſes be rightly applyed.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1. <hi>The firſt means to get into the new birth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe means to get into <hi>the new birth,</hi> is firſt <hi>Examination;</hi> and the way to examine, is to ſet before men that Chryſtal glaſs of the Law for their <hi>light and rule:</hi> To this purpoſe I have here annexed a <hi>Catalogue,</hi> or Table, to ſhew them their offences; not that I can poſſibly ennumerate all ſins, but onely the kindes; and if herein I come ſhort, yet conſciences awaked may be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned hereby to bring into their thoughts thoſe others not mentioned.</p>
                  <p>Now then (whoſoever thou art that beginn'ſt this bleſſed work) examine thy ſelf by this <hi>Catalogue,</hi> but do it warily, and truly, and where thou find'ſt thy ſelf guilty, either note it in this book, or tranſcribe it into ſome paper, that ſo they may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for thine eye when thou comeſt to <hi>Confeſsion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:30627:30"/>
                  <head>Sect. 2. <hi>Sins againſt the firſt Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN every Commandment we muſt obſerve both the duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and ſins forbidden, for both theſe are implyed in every one of the Commandments; if in the firſt thou art guilty, thou muſt anſwer negatively; if in the ſecond, thou muſt anſwer affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively: now then to proceed.</p>
                  <p>It is the firſt Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other gods but me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required,</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, Haſt thou ever in minde, will, and affections, took the true God in Chriſt to be thy God? Secondly, haſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in thoſe graces by which thou ſhouldſt cleave unto God, as in the warmth of knowledge, and love, and fear, and joy, and truſting in God? Thirdly, haſt thou obſerved Gods mercies, and promiſes, and works, and judgements upon thee, and (by a particular application) took ſpecial notice thereof? Fourthly, haſt thou communicated with the godly, and joyned thy ſelf to Gods people, and delighted chiefly in them?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden,</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, haſt thou not ſometimes been guilty of blaſphemy, or idolatry, or witchcraft, or atheiſm, or epicuriſm, or hereſie? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, haſt thou not been guilty of pride, a ſin flatly oppoſing God, and firſt committed by devils? Thirdly, haſt thou not had inward reaſonings that <hi>there is no God,</hi> or that <hi>he ſeeth not,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1. Eſay 29.15. Iob 21.14. Ier. 17.5.</note> 
                        <hi>or knoweth not, or that there is no profit in his ſervice?</hi> Fourthly, haſt thou not failed to love God, and fear God, and to put thy whole truſt in God? Fifthly, haſt thou not <hi>truſted in man,</hi> or <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man,</hi> or <hi>loved the world,</hi> and thereby alienated thy heart from God? Sixthly, haſt thou not <hi>reſorted to witches,</hi> or in the firſt place <hi>to Phyſitians,</hi> and not to the living God? Seventhly, haſt thou not <hi>tempted God,</hi> and in the matters of God, been either cold or lukewarm, or prepoſterouſly zealous? Eighthly, haſt thou not a proneneſs to ſin, yea to rebel againſt God in thy whole man? Ninthly, haſt thou not been careleſs to perform the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward duties of <hi>Gods worſhip in ſincerity and truth?</hi> if in theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broken this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no gods but me.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:30627:31"/>
                  <head>Sect. 3. <hi>Sins againſt the ſecond Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the ſecond Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image.</hi>]</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, haſt thou ever worſhipped the true God purely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will? Secondly, haſt thou obſerved all thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward duties of his worſhip, as prayer, and vows, and faſting, and meditating, and the reſt? Thirdly, haſt thou repaired to Gods houſe, obſerved family duties, received the Preachers of the Goſpel?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden.</head>
                     <p>Say firſt,
<note place="margin">Ier 9.14.</note> haſt thou not ſometimes <hi>walked after the imaginations of thy own heart,</hi> ſerving God out of cuſtom, or (after the maner of thy fore-fathers) by will-worſhip and ſuperſtitions? Secondly, haſt thou not committed <hi>idol worſhip,</hi> conceiving of God in thy minde, or reſpecting him in thy ſenſe in the likeneſs of a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?
<note place="margin">Exod 23.13.</note> Thirdly, haſt thou not <hi>mentioned the names of other gods,</hi> either by way of ſwearing, or apology? Fourthly, haſt thou not made an image to <hi>liken God to it,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eſay 40.18.</note> or uſed any geſture of love and reverence to any ſuch images? Fifthly, in a word, haſt thou not been careleſs <hi>to worſhip God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Zach. 14.17. Pſal. 14.4. Math. 10.14.</note> 
                        <hi>to call upon the Lord, to receive Gods Miniſters,</hi> or to perform any other of the outward duties of Gods worſhip? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broken this Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 4. <hi>Sins againſt the third Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the third Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain.</hi>]</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties required:</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, haſt thou been ever a conſtant learner, hearer, and doer of Gods Word and Will? Secondly, haſt thou prayed with perſeverance, underſtanding, and power of the Spirit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting or wavering? Thirdly, haſt thou come preparedly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30627:31"/>to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and <hi>being come, haſt thou diſcerned the Lords body?</hi> Fourthly, haſt thou uſed all the titles, and properties, and works, and ordinances of the Lord with knowledge, faith, reverence, joy, and ſincerity?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden:</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, haſt thou not ſometimes in thy talk diſhonored the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, attributes, religion, word, people of God, or any thing that hath in it the print of his holineſs? Secondly, haſt thou not ſworn or forſworn, or <hi>loved falſe oathes?</hi> Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Zach 8.17.</note> haſt thou not cauſed the name of religion, or people of God to be evil thought of by thy ill courſe of life, or by committing ſome groſs ſin? Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, haſt thou not raſhly, or unpreparedly, or heedleſly read the Word, heard Sermons, received the Sacraments, or performed any other part of the worſhip of God? Fifthly, haſt thou not thought or ſpoken blaſphemouſly, or contemptuouſly of God, or of any thing whatſoever pertaining to God? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broken this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 5. <hi>Sins againſt the fourth Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the fourth Commandement, <hi>Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, haſt thou (according to the equity of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment) ever obſerved <hi>the Lords day,</hi> and other days and times ſet apart for Gods ſervice? Secondly, haſt thou on thoſe days reſted from the ſervile works of ſin, and reſted and relyed upon Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſins, and led an holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious life, that ſo thou <hi>mayeſt enter into that reſt of heaven?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 4.11.</note> Thirdly, haſt thou always prepared thy heart, before thou went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt into the houſe of the Lord, by meditation of Gods Word and Works, by examination and reformation of thy ways, by prayer, thankſgiving, and holy reſolution to carry thy ſelf as in Gods preſence, and to hear and obey whatſoever thou ſhouldſt learn out of the pure Word of God? Fourthly, haſt thou repaired to Gods houſe in due time, and ſtayed the whole time of Prayer,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30627:32"/>reading, preaching of the Word, ſinging of Pſalms, receiving of the Sacraments? Fifthly, haſt thou performed private religious offices upon the Lords day, to wit, <hi>In private prayer and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, in acknowledging thy offences to God, in reconciling thy ſelf to thoſe thou haſt offended, or with whom thou art at variance; in viſiting the ſick, comforting the afflicted, contributing to the neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the poor, inſtructing thy Children and ſervants</hi> (and the reſt of thy family) <hi>in the fear and nurture of the Lord?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden:</head>
                     <p>Say firſt, haſt thou not ſometime ſpent the Lords day in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 46.10.</note> or in wordly buſineſs, in vanities, or in ſin? Secondly, haſt thou not omitted publique duties, or comeſt in too late, or went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt out too ſoon?
<note place="margin">Nehem. 10.31. and 13.15.</note> Thirdly, haſt thou not on thoſe days <hi>ſold wares, carried burthens, brought in ſheaves,</hi> or <hi>wrought in the harveſt?</hi> Fourthly, haſt thou not employed thy cattel, or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or children, or any other, though thou workeſt not thy ſelf? Fifthly, haſt thou not profaned the Lords day, by needleſs works, words, or thoughts, about thy calling, or about thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation? Sixthly, have not the ſtrict obſervance of the duties of that day been tedious unto thee, ſaying in thine heart, <hi>When will the day be gone?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Amos 8.5.</note> If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broken this Commandment, <hi>Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath day.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 6. <hi>Sins againſt the fifth Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the fifth Commandment, <hi>Honor thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>For the duties here required, they are either in
<list>
                        <item>Family.</item>
                        <item>Common-weal.</item>
                        <item>Church.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.25. 1 Pet. 3.7.</note> for the Family: Say, if thou art an husband; 1. Haſt thou ever loved thy wife, <hi>and dealt with her according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, giving honor to her as to the weaker veſſel, and as being heirs together of the grace of life, that your prayers were not hindred?</hi> If thou art a wife:
<note place="margin">Eph 5.22, 24. 1 Pet. 3.4.</note> 2. <hi>Haſt thou ſubmitted to thine own huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as unto the Lord in every thing?</hi> 3. <hi>Haſt thou put on the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30627:32"/>of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price?</hi> If thou art a parent: 4.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Haſt thou brought up thy children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord?</hi> 5. <hi>Haſt thou corrected them, yet not provoked them by immoderate correction?</hi> 6. <hi>Haſt thou provided for them</hi> in their callings,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 5.8. Rom. 1.30.</note> or outward eſtates? If thou art a childe: 7. <hi>Haſt thou obeyed thy parents, and received correction with ſubmiſsion and reverence?</hi> 8.
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Haſt thou relieved them in their wants?</hi> 9. <hi>Haſt thou obſerved their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and covered their infirmities?</hi> If thou art a maſter: 10. Haſt thou entertained <hi>Gods ſervants,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 15.15. Gen. 9.22. Col. 4.1. Tit. 2.9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>and given unto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant that which is juſt and equal?</hi> If thou art a ſervant: 11. <hi>Haſt thou been obedient to thy maſter according to the fleſh, with fear and trembling, in ſingleneſs of heart, as unto Chriſt? Not anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, not purloyning, but ſhewing all good fidelity?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, for the Common-weal; if thou art a Magiſtrate, 12. Haſt thou <hi>executed</hi> juſt laws? 13. Haſt thou reformed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers abuſes, <hi>according to the power that is in thee?</hi> If thou art a Subject: 14. Haſt thou obeyed the higher Powers in all juſt commands? 15. Haſt thou been <hi>ſubject unto them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> 
                     <hi>not onely for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for the Church; If thou art a Miniſter: 16. Haſt thou <hi>taught in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon?</hi> 17. Hath <hi>thy light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before men, that they might ſee thy good works?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 5.16. Gal. 6.6 Heb 13 7, 17, 18.</note> If thou art a hearer: 18. Haſt thou <hi>communicated to them that teach thee in all good things?</hi> 19. Haſt thou <hi>obeyed them, and prayed for them, and loved them, and followed them, conſidering the end of their converſation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden,</head>
                     <p>And firſt for the Family: Say, if thou art an husband: 1.
<note place="margin">Prov. 21.19.</note> Haſt thou not ſometimes abuſed thy wife, or ſmitten her, or injured her, in thought, word, or deed? If thou art a wife: 2. Haſt thou not been waſteful, or froward, or idle? If thou art a childe: 3. Haſt thou not <hi>deſpiſed thy fathers or mothers inſtructions?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prov. 15.5. Prov. 30.17. and 20.20.</note> 4. Haſt thou not mocked <hi>them, or deſpiſed them, or curſed them, or ſmitten them, or ſhamed them,</hi> or grieved them? If thou art a maſter: 5. Haſt thou not governed thy family negligently? 6. Haſt thou not with-held that which is juſt and equal in diet, wages, encouragement? If thou art a ſervant: 7. Haſt thou not been idle, and ſlothful? 8. Haſt thou not ſerved grudgingly, and not from the heart?</p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:30627:33"/>
                     <p>Secondly, for the Common-weal: If thou art a Magiſtrate: 9. Haſt thou not been as a Lyon, or a <hi>Bear, roaring and ranging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the poor people?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prov. 28.15. Eſa. 10.1.</note> 10. <hi>Haſt thou not decreed unrighteous decrees? reſpecting the perſons of the poor, or honoring the perſons of the mighty?</hi> If thou art a Subject: 11. Haſt thou not reviled <hi>the Gods,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Levit. 19.15. Exod. 12.28. Rom. 13.1, 7.</note> 
                        <hi>or curſed the Ruler of thy people?</hi> 12. Haſt thou not <hi>diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the higher Powers, or not denied tribute, or cuſtom, or honor, or fear to whom they are due?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, for the Church; if thou art a Miniſter: 13. Haſt thou not been <hi>prophane and wicked in thy life and converſation?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ierem. 23.11.</note> 14. <hi>Haſt thou not run before thou waſt ſent?</hi> or being ſent, haſt thou not been <hi>negligent in the gift that is in thee?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14. Ierem. 23.13.</note> 16. Haſt thou not <hi>propheſied in Baal, and cauſed Gods people to erre?</hi> 17. Haſt thou not <hi>committed ſimony,</hi> or ſought <hi>indirectly</hi> for the fleece, not regarding reſpectively the <hi>flock?</hi> 18. Haſt thou not ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>the hands of evil doers,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ierem. 23.14.</note> in preaching peace to wicked men? 19. Haſt thou <hi>not given heed to fables</hi> (or to ſome <hi>unprofitable matter) rather than to godly edifying,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.4.</note> which is <hi>in faith?</hi> If thou art an hearer: 20 Haſt thou not reſiſted the Miniſter, and the Word preached by him?
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.6. Heb. 13.7, 17, 18.</note> whatſoever thou art, <hi>husband, or wife, or parent, or childe, or maſter, or ſervant, or Magiſtrate, or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or Miniſter, or hearer,</hi> if in any of theſe thou haſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, then haſt thou broke this Commandment, <hi>Honor thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy mother.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 7. <hi>Sins againſt the ſixth Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the ſixth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say, 1. Haſt thou ever deſired and ſtudied by all means law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to preſerve thine own perſon, and the perſon of thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden.</head>
                     <p>Say: 1 Haſt thou not ſometimes envied others for their <hi>wealth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen 26.14. Numb. 11.29. Gen. 37.11. Iob 16 9</note> or for their <hi>gifts,</hi> or for their <hi>reſpects</hi> with others? 2. Haſt thou not offended others in geſtures, <hi>gnaſhing on them with thy teeth, or ſharpening thine eyes on them?</hi> 3. Haſt thou not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30627:33"/>fended others in words, by cenſuring, or <hi>reviling,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.9. Pſal. 37.12.</note> or <hi>rendring evil for evil,</hi> or <hi>railing for railing?</hi> 4. Haſt thou not offended others in deeds, <hi>plotting againſt the just,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Matth. 5.22, Amos 2.11.</note> or doing evil to any man? 5. Haſt thou not been angry with thy brother without cauſe, or continued long in anger, <hi>keeping thy wrath</hi> (as it were) <hi>for ever?</hi> 6. Haſt thou not <hi>rejoyced at others fall,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 24.17. Iob 31.30.</note> or <hi>wiſhed a curſe to their ſouls?</hi> 7. Haſt thou not done evil to thy ſelf, by inordinate fretting, or grieving, or drinking, or ſurfetting,
<note place="margin">Numb. 14.2. Pro. 6.14.</note> or ſaying in thy paſſions, <hi>Would God I were dead?</hi> 8. Haſt thou not been <hi>a ſower of diſcord,</hi> or ſome way or other, a juſt occaſion of the diſcomfort, or of the death of thy neighbor? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, thou haſt then broken this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 8. <hi>Sins againſt the ſeventh Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the ſeventh Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say: Haſt thou ever kept thy ſelf pure in ſoul and body, both towards thy ſelf and others?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden.</head>
                     <p>Say: Haſt thou not ſometimes been defiled with buggery, Sodomitry, inceſt, whoredom, adultery, Polygamy,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.26.</note> ſelf-polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or with changing <hi>the natural uſe into that which is againſt nature?</hi> 2. Haſt thou not offended in the occaſions of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as in idleneſs, gluttony, drunkenneſs, wanton company, whoriſh attire, or perfumes? 3.
<note place="margin">Pro. 7.16, 17. Col. 3.8.</note> Haſt thou not ſinned in thy ſenſes, or geſtures, or words, by <hi>filthy communication proceeding out of thy mouth?</hi> 4. Haſt thou not harbored in thy heart burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing luſts, <hi>impure thoughts, inordinate affections?</hi> 5.
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.28.</note> Haſt thou not behaved thy ſelf immodeſtly, unſoberly,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> or ſhameleſly abuſing <hi>thy body,</hi> or uſing ſome maner of dalliance and wantonneſs? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broken this Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:30627:34"/>
                  <head>Sect. 9. <hi>Sins againſt the eighth Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the eighth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say, Haſt thou ever, by all good means, furthered the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate of thy ſelf and of thy neighbor?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden.</head>
                     <p>Say: Firſt, Haſt thou not ſometimes got thy living by an unlawful calling? Secondly, haſt thou not impoveriſht thy ſelf by idleneſs, luxurious, or unneceſſary expences? Thirdly, haſt thou not withheld from thy ſelf, or others, that which ſhould have been expended? Fourthly, haſt thou not gotten, or kept thy neighbors goods by falſhood, or force, and made no reſtitution? Fifthly, haſt thou not ſtollen by uſury, or oppreſſion, or fraud, in buying or ſelling, an abomination unto the Lord? Sixthly, haſt thou not <hi>robbed God of his tythes and offerings</hi> by ſacriledge or ſymony?
<note place="margin">Deut. 25.16. Malac. 3.8.</note> Seventhly, haſt thou not ſome way or other impaired thy neighbors ſtate? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, then haſt thou broken this Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 10. <hi>Sins againſt the ninth Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the ninth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say, Haſt thou ever by all means ſought to maintain thy own and thy neighbors good name, according to truth and a good conſcience?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden.</head>
                     <p>Say,
<note place="margin">Rev. 22.15.</note> Firſt, haſt thou not ſometimes loved (or made) <hi>a lye?</hi> Secondly,
<note place="margin">Ier. 20.10. Mat. 7.3. Prov. 24.24.</note> haſt thou not <hi>raiſed a falſe report, to the defaming of many?</hi> Thirdly, haſt thou not <hi>cenſured or judged others, yet never conſidered the beam that is in thy own eye?</hi> Fourthly, haſt thou not flattered thy ſelf and others, <hi>ſaying unto the wicked, Thou art righteous?</hi> Fifthly, haſt thou not condemned ſome without wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30627:34"/>or forborn to witneſs for others when thou kneweſt the truth? Sixthly, haſt thou not been uncharitably ſuſpitious, or <hi>a deſpiſer of thy neighbor?</hi> Seventhly, haſt thou not told a lye, whether jeſtingly, or officiouſly, or perniciouſly? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broke this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 11. <hi>Sins againſt the laſt Commandment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is the laſt Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>]</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>For the duties here required.</head>
                     <p>Say, Firſt, haſt thou ever been truly contented with thy own outward condition? Secondly, haſt thou rejoyced at others good, and <hi>loved thy neighbor as thy ſelf?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Matth. 19.19.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or for the ſins here forbidden.</head>
                     <p>Say, Firſt,
<note place="margin">Matth. 15.19.</note> haſt thou not ſometimes conceived <hi>evil thoughts in thy heart?</hi> Secondly, haſt thou not delighted in the inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations of evil? Thirdly, haſt thou not been full of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with thy own condition and ſtate? Fourthly, haſt thou not felt <hi>another law of thy members warring againſt the law of thy minde?</hi> Fifthly,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.29.</note> haſt thou not coveted after ſomething or other that was thy neighbors, either with will, or by actual concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence? If in any of theſe thou haſt tranſgreſſed, then haſt thou broke this Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The ſecond means to get into the new birth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter <hi>examination</hi> (which may well ſerve thee for one days work or two) the next duty is <hi>Confeſſion.</hi> Now then take the Catalogue of thoſe ſins (or if thy awaked conſcience can tell thee of any other) which thou knoweſt thou haſt committed, and noted, either in this book, or on ſome other paper; and kneeling on thy knees, ſpread thy Catalogue before the Lord, I ſay, ſpread thy Catalogue before the Lord,
<note place="margin">2 King 19.14</note> as <hi>Hezekiah did his letter;</hi> there read thou ſeriouſly and particularly, ſaying, <hi>O Lord, I confeſs I have committed this ſin, and the other ſin</hi> [as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30627:35"/>they are before thee in order] <hi>of all theſe ſins I am guilty, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of thoſe ſins wherein I delighted, my darlings, my minions, my boſom-ſins,</hi> [take notice of them, and confeſs them again] <hi>of all theſe ſins I am guilty; And now, O Lord, ſtanding (as it were) at the bar of thy tribunal, I arraign my ſelf, and accuſe my ſelf, and judge my ſelf worthy of the utmoſt of thy wrath and indignation; for one ſin thou caſt Adam out of paradiſe, for one ſin thou cast the Angels out of heaven, for one ſin thou deſtroyedſt a world of men, and what then ſhall become of me, that have committed a world of ſins?</hi>—[here pauſe a while, and meditate on thy unworthineſs.] <hi>O that I ſhould be ſo fooliſh, ſo bruitiſh, ſo mad to commit theſe ſins, theſe manifold ſins! O that by theſe ſins I ſhould break ſo holy a law, provoke ſo good and great a Majeſty! What ſhall I do, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring my evil ways,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 36.31.</note> 
                  <hi>even loath my ſelf in my own ſight (yea abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes) for my iniquities and my abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? &amp;c.</hi>—For concluſion, thou mayſt imitate the Publican, who not daring to <hi>lift up his eyes, ſmote his breſt,</hi> ſo do thou, and ſigh,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.13.</note> and ſay with him, <hi>O God be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1. <hi>The third means to get into the new birth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter <hi>Confeſsion</hi> (which may well ſerve thee for another days work) the next duty thou muſt labor for, is to ſeek for true ſorrow and mourning for thy ſins: Seek thou muſt, and never leave ſeeking, till thou feel thy heart melt within thee. To this purpoſe reade ſome tracts of death, of judgement, of hell, of Chriſts paſſion, of the joys of heaven: Laſt of all (and I take it beſt of all) reſolve to <hi>ſet every day ſome time apart to beg it of the Lord:</hi> When <hi>Daniel</hi> ſet himſelf to pray, the Lord came in to him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.3. When <hi>Peter</hi> had gone apart to pray; and when <hi>Paul</hi> had prayed in the Temple, then the Lord came in to them, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.6. <hi>and</hi> 22.17. And why may not I bid thee pray, as well as <hi>Peter</hi> bid <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> yet <hi>being in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and bond of iniquity?</hi> Act. 8.22, 23. and at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed fall down on thy knees, ſpread thy Catalogue, confeſs,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30627:35"/>accuſe, judge, condemn thy ſelf again; which done, beg, beg of the Lord to give thee that ſoft <hi>heart</hi> he promiſed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 36.26.</note> 
                     <hi>A new heart will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the ſtony heart out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh.</hi> Say then to thy ſelf, <hi>Is this the Lords promiſe? O Lord perform it to my heart; take away my ſtony heart, give me an heart of fleſh, a new heart, a new ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi>—[here make thine own prayer, be not careful of words, onely let the words be the true voice of thy heart:] and the more to work ſoftning, thou mayeſt ſob, and ſigh, and beat thy breſt, above all thou muſt pray, and call, and cry with vehemency and fervency not to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. When thou haſt done, if the Lord do not yet hear thee, pray again the next day, and the next day, yea put on this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, that thou wilt never leave praying till the Lord hear thee in mercy, till he make thee to feel thy heart <hi>melt</hi> within thee, yea (if it may be) till thou ſeeſt thy
<note n="*" place="margin">Ut hoc modo confring as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pita draconum tuorum in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis.</note> 
                     <hi>tears trickling down thy cheeks,</hi> becauſe of thy offences. The Lord will (perhaps) hear thee at the firſt time, or at the ſecond time; or if he do not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt thou, thy ſuit is juſt, and importunity will prevail; yea I can ſay, <hi>thy deſire to ſorrow being reſolute, it is a degree of godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it ſelf,</hi> and no doubt the Lord will increaſe it, if thou begſt hard a while.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 2. <hi>The firſt reaſon for this ſorrow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis muſt be done, firſt becauſe <hi>without pangs no birth: Quid ſunt dolores parturientis niſi dolores poenitentis?</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin) the pangs of a penitent man are as the pangs of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 48.</note> Now as there can be no birth without pains of travel go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before, ſo neither true repentance without ſome terrors of the law, and ſtraits of conſcience.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye have not received the ſpirit of bondage again to fear,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle to the Romans; and what is that? but to ſhew us, they once did receive it; when? but in the very firſt preparation to converſion: then it was that the Spirit of God in the law did ſo bear witneſs unto them of their <hi>bondage,</hi> that it made them to <hi>fear.</hi> And certainly thus it is with every man in his firſt converſion, his contrition muſt be compungent, and vehement, bruiſing, breaking, renting the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30627:36"/>heart, and feeling the throws (as a woman laboring of childe) before there can be a <hi>new birth,</hi> or <hi>the new creature</hi> be brought forth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 3. <hi>The ſecond reaſon for this ſorrow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AGain, <hi>without contrition no Chriſt;</hi> therefore it was that God firſt opened the eyes of our firſt parents, to make them ſee and be ſenſible of their ſin and miſery,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.7, 15. <hi>Chryſoſt. in c.</hi> 3 <hi>Matth. hom.</hi> 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.7. before he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Chriſt, verſ. 15. therefore it was that <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome) firſt throughly frighted the mindes of his hearers with the terror of judgement, and expectation of torment, and with the name of an axe, and their rejection, and entertainment of other children, and by doubling the puniſhment, to wit, of being hewn down, and caſt into the fire; and when he had thus every way tamed, and taken down their ſtubbornneſs, then at length he makes mention of Chriſt. Why, then is Chriſt ſeaſonably revealed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Muſculus) when the hearts of men being ſoundly pierced by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repentance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Muſc. in Mat. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect. Tunc. accedit Ieſus. Calvin in Eſay</hi> 61.</note> 
                     <hi>are poſſeſſed with a deſire of his gracious righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Or if you will hear <hi>Calvin, To whom is Chriſt promiſed, but to them alone who are humbled and confounded with the ſenſe of their own ſins?</hi> Certainly the firſt thing that draws to Chriſt, is to conſider our miſerable eſtate without him; No man will come to Chriſt except he be hungry; no man will take Chriſts yoke upon him, till he come to know and feel the weight of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans yoke; to this end therefore muſt every man be broken with threats, and ſcourges, and laſhes of conſcience, that ſo deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelf he may flye unto Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 4. <hi>The third reaſon for this ſorrow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AGain,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.10.</note> 
                     <hi>without hearty ſorrow no ſpiritual comfort.</hi> We muſt firſt be <hi>humbled before the Lord,</hi> and then he will lift us up. Chriſt indeed was anointed to preach good tidings, but to whom? <hi>to the poor, to the broken-hearted, to the captives, to them that are bound,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 61.11.</note> 
                     <hi>to the bruiſed,</hi> Eſay 61.11. God pours not the oyl of his mercy ſave into a broken veſſel, God never comforts
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30627:36"/>throughly, ſave where he findes humiliation and repentance for ſin.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Forbes</hi> on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. c. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>The word of God</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>hath three degrees of operation in the hearts of his choſen: Firſt, it falleth to mens ears as the ſound of many waters, a mighty, great, and confuſed ſound, and which commonly bringeth neither terror nor joy, but yet a wondring, and acknowledgement of a ſtrange force, and more then humane power; this is that effect which many felt hearing Chriſt, when they were aſtoniſhed at his doctrine, as teaching with authority;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 1.22, 27. Luke 4.32. Iohn 7.46.</note> 
                     <hi>what maner doctrine is this? never man ſpake like this man: The next effect is the voice of thunder, which bringeth not onely wonder, but fear alſo; not onely filleth the ears with ſound, and the heart with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but moreover ſhaketh and terrifieth the conſcience: The third effect is the ſound of harping, while the word not onely raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with admiration, and ſtriketh the conſcience with terror, but alſo laſtly filleth it with ſweet peace and joy. Now albeit the two firſt degrees may be without the laſt, yet none feel the laſt, who have not in ſome degree felt both the firſt.</hi> He ſaith true, <hi>in ſome degree,</hi> though commonly the deeper is the ſenſe of miſery, the ſweeter is the ſenſe of mercy. In our dead ſecurity <hi>before converſion</hi> (ſaith another) <hi>God is fain to let the law, ſin, conſcience, Satan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Boltons</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</note> 
                     <hi>a deep ſenſe of our abominable and curſed ſtate looſe upon us, and to kindle the very fire of hell in our ſouls, that ſo we might be rouzed, and afterward more ſweetly and ſoundly raiſed and refreſhed; for after the moſt toylſome labor is the ſweeteſt ſleep, after the greateſt tempeſts the ſtilleſt calms; ſanctified troubles and terrors eſtabliſh the ſureſt peace, and the ſhaking of theſe winds makes the trees of Gods Eden take the better rooting.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1. <hi>The means to be delivered out of the pangs of the new birth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ANd now if (by Gods bleſſing) thou feeleſt this ſorrow and <hi>melting of heart,</hi> the next thing thou muſt do is to ſeek for the remedy, which remedy conſiſts of theſe ingredients: Firſt, <hi>A ſight of Chriſt;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>A deſire after Chriſt;</hi> thirdly, <hi>A rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Chriſt;</hi> fourthly, <hi>An obedience to Chriſt;</hi> fifthly, <hi>A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30627:37"/>in Chriſt ſought for and obtained.</hi> Thou wilt ſay, theſe ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients are pearls indeed, but how ſhould I procure them? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by application of the promiſes; and ſith every ingredient hath its particular promiſes, I ſhall let thee ſee them in order, onely do thou apply them thy ſelf; it is enough for the Phyſitian to prepare the medicine, thy own body muſt receive it; ſo in this medicine it is, thou muſt apply it if thou wilt have ſouls<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>health.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 2. <hi>The promiſes procuring a ſight of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe firſt ſtep or ingredient that brings comfort to thy heavy ſoul, is <hi>the ſight of Chriſt:</hi> and to procure this <hi>ſight,</hi> thou haſt theſe promiſes:</p>
                  <p>Matth. 1.21. <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name Jeſus, for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Luke 2.10, 11. <hi>Behold I bring you good tidings of great joy that ſhall be to all people, that is, that unto you is born this day in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of David a Savior, which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>John 1.29. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God which taketh away the ſins of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>John 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, to the end that all that believe in him ſhould not periſh, but have life everlaſting.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>John 3.17. <hi>God ſent not his Son into the world that he ſhould condemn the world, but that the world through him might be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rom. 3.25. <hi>God hath ſet forth Chriſt Jeſus to be a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through faith in his blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Cor. 1.30. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus of God is made unto us wiſdom, and righteouſneſs, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>This is a true ſaying, and by all means worthy to be received, that Chriſt Jeſus came in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o the world to ſave ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Heb. 13.12. <hi>Jeſus, that he might ſanctifie the people with his own blood, ſuffered without the gate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 John. 2.1, 2. <hi>If any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for us onely, but alſo the ſins of the whole world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Revel. 5.8. <hi>Thou waſt killed, and haſt redeemed us to God by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30627:37"/>thy blood, out of every kindred, and tongue, and people, and nation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All theſe tell thee, that as thou art a ſinner, ſo thou haſt a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior; onely do thou apply them, and certainly they will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thee the firſt ſtep, the firſt ingredient of this remedy to thy miſery, to wit, <hi>the ſight of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 3. <hi>The promiſes procuring a deſire after Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THou mayſt ſay, <hi>I ſee Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>I ſee</hi> that his perſon, and death, and blood-ſhed, are precious and ſaving; but how may I make him mine? how may I know that he is my Savior? I anſwer, thou muſt <hi>hunger and thirſt after him;</hi> this <hi>deſire</hi> is the ſecond ſtep: and to provoke thee to this duty, conſider of theſe promiſes:</p>
                  <p>Eſay 55.1. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money, come ye, buy and eat, yea come, buy wine and milk without money, and without price.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mat. 5.6. <hi>Bleſſed are they which hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, for they ſhall be filled.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>John 7.37, 38. <hi>In the laſt day, that great day of the feaſt, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſtood and cried, ſaying, If any man thirſt, let him come unto me and drink; he that believeth on me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Revel. 21.6. <hi>I will give to him that is athirſt, of the water of life freely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Revel. 22.17. <hi>Let him that is athirſt come, and whoſoever will, let him take the water of life freely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pſal. 63.1. <hi>O God, thou art my God, early will I ſeek thee, my ſoul thirſteth for thee, my fleſh longeth greatly after thee, in a barren and dry land without water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pſal. 145.19. <hi>He will fulfil the deſire of them that fear him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All theſe may provoke thee to thirſt after Chriſt, that moſt ſoveraign, and ſoul ſaving <hi>fountain, opened to the houſe of David, and to the inhabitants of Jeruſalem for ſin, and for uncleanneſs,</hi> Zach. 13.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30627:38"/>
                  <head>Sect. 4. <hi>The promiſes procuring a relying on Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>YEt thou mayeſt ſay, <hi>I thirſt</hi> indeed, but I dare not drink; <hi>I deſire,</hi> but I dare not come neer, to <hi>lay hold</hi> on Chriſt: How ſo? <hi>I am</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>a moſt vile, unworthy, wicked wretch, and my ſins are of a ſcarlet, crimſon die:</hi> True it is; for thee to pretend part in Chriſt, wallowing yet in thy ſins, for thee to believe that Chriſt is thy righteouſneſs, purpoſing yet to go on in the practice, or allowance of any one known ſin, it were a moſt curſed horrible preſumption indeed; but where all ſin is a burthen, every promiſe as a world of gold, and the heart ſincere for a <hi>new</hi> way, there a man may be bold: A man may? yes, he muſt; if thou groaneſt under ſin, if thou longeſt after Chriſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe promiſes, and they will force thee to lay hold upon the Rock, to take Chriſt for thine own, to throw thy ſinful ſoul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bleeding wounds of Jeſus, and to caſt thy ſelf with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence into the boſom of his love.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Boltons</hi> Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctions for afflicted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> 
                     <hi>Take notice</hi> (ſaith a Modern) <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt keeps open houſe for all hungry and thirſty ſouls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Revel. 22.17. <hi>Let him that is athirſt come, and whoſoever will, let him take the water of life freely.</hi> Or if open houſe will not fit without invitation, hear him call;</p>
                  <p>Matth. 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labor, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Or if invitation will not fit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proclamation, hear him proclaim:</p>
                  <p>Joh. 7.37. <hi>Jeſus ſtood and cryed, ſaying, If any man thirſt, let him come unto me and drink: he that believeth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of water.</hi> Or leaſt thou ſhouldeſt think thou muſt come to thy coſt, and bring ſomewhat in thy hand, hear how he doubles and trebbles his cry to the contrary:</p>
                  <p>Iſa. 55.1. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money, come ye, buy and eat, yea come, buy wine and milk without money, and without price.</hi> And yet leſt thou ſay, I am ſo far from bringing any thing in my hand, that I bring a world of wickedneſs in my heart, and my ſins I fear will hinder my acceptation, no (ſaith he again)</p>
                  <p>Iſa. 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30627:38"/>man his thoughts</hi> (and this is thy deſire, thy caſe) <hi>and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi> Or if all this will not do without a more ſolemn invitation, ſee then how the Lord of heaven ſends forth his Embaſſadors to move thee, and entreat thee to come in:</p>
                  <p>2 Cor. 5.20. <hi>Now then we are Embaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconciled unto God.</hi> Or if he cannot woo thee, lo he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands thee:</p>
                  <p>1 Ioh. 3.23. <hi>And this is the Commandment, that we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on the name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Or yet to drive thee to Chriſt, he not onely commands, but threatens:</p>
                  <p>Heb. 3.18. <hi>And to whom ſware he that they ſhould not enter into his reſt, but to them that believed not?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what can he do more unto his Vineyard? Firſt (to bid thee welcom) he keeps open houſe; ſecondly, he invites; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he proclaims; fourthly, he calls thee <hi>ſans-fee,</hi> without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or moneyworth; fifthly, he apologizeth; ſixthly, he ſendeth; ſeventhly, he commandeth; eighthly, he threatneth: Hear what mine Author concludes from theſe premiſes; <hi>How cruel then is that man to his own wounded conſcience, who in his extreme ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual thirſt will not be drawn by this eight-fold merciful cord, to drink his fill of the fountain of the water of life, to caſt himſelf with confidence and comfort into the arms of the Lord Ieſus? — Yea, how is it poſſible, but that all, or ſome of theſe, ſhould bring in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry broken heart to believe, and every one that is weary of his ſins, to relye upon the Lord of life for everlasting welfare?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 5. <hi>The promiſes procuring obedience to Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ANd yet thou mayeſt ſay, <hi>I have caſt my ſelf on Chriſt,</hi> is this all I muſt do? no, there is yet another ſtep, he is not onely to be thy Savior, but thy husband, thou muſt love him, and ſerve him, and honor him, and obey him: thou muſt endeavor not onely for pardon of ſin, and ſalvation from hell, but for purity, new obedience, ability to do or ſuffer any thing for Chriſt. And to provoke thee to this duty, conſider of theſe texts:</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:30627:39"/>
                  <p>Matth. 7.21. <hi>Not every one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of heaven, but he that doth the will of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Matth. 11.29. <hi>Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart, and ye ſhall finde reſt unto your ſouls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Matth. 16.24. <hi>If any man will follow me, let him take up his croſs and follow me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2 Cor. 5.15. <hi>He dyed for all, that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelvs, but unto him which dyed for them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2 Cor. 5.17. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, let him be a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, old things are paſſed, behold all things are become new.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Joh. 1.6, 7. <hi>If we ſay that we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſs, we lye, and do not the truth. But if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Joh. 2.5, 6. <hi>He that keepeth his word, in him verily is the love of God perfected, hereby know we that we are in him. He that ſaith, he abideth in him, ought himſelf alſo ſo to walk, even as he walked.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Joh. 3.6, 9. <hi>Whoſoever abideth in him, ſinneth not. — Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is born of God, doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Joh. 3.24. <hi>He that keepeth his Commandments, dwelleth in him, and hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1 Joh. 5.18. <hi>We know that whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not, but he that is begotten of God keepeth himſelf, and that wicked one toucheth him not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All theſe may invite thee to enter into the <hi>holy path,</hi> and to fight under Chriſts banner againſt the world, the fleſh, and the Devil, unto thy lives end.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 6. <hi>The promiſes procuring comfort in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ONce more thou mayeſt ſay, <hi>I have been truly humbled with the ſenſe of ſin, and ſenſe of miſery, and ſorrow for ſin; yea, I have ſeen, and thirſted, and relyed, and purpoſed univerſal obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30627:39"/>to my Savior, and yet no comfort comes:</hi> it may be ſo, but haſt thou praiſed God for this work of wonder, <hi>the new birth</hi> wrought in thee? If ſo, then is there another duty expected from thee, right precious and pleaſing unto God, and that is <hi>waiting:</hi> yet I could wiſh thee addreſs thy ſelf to theſe precious <hi>promiſes,</hi> ſettle thy ſoul on them with fixed meditation and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer, and where thou perceiveſt the <hi>condition of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> to be by Gods grace formed in thee, thou mayeſt ſafely aſſure thy ſoul of ſo much favor, as is expreſly contained in the <hi>promiſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Levit. 26.40, 41, 42, 44. <hi>If they ſhall confeſs their iniquity, — If their uncircumciſed hearts be humbled, — Then will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my Covenant, — that I might be their God, I am the Lord:</hi> the condition is to confeſs and be humbled; and this if thou doſt, the Covenant is ſure, <hi>the Lord is thy God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Job 33.27, 28. <hi>If any ſay, I have ſinned, and perverted that which is right, and it profited me not; he will deliver his ſoul from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light.</hi> The condition is, <hi>If any ſay, I have ſinned,</hi> if thy heart ſay thus in ſincerity and truth, the promiſe is ſure, <hi>God will deliver thy ſoul</hi> from hell, and thou <hi>ſhalt ſee the light of heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pſal. 51.17. <hi>A broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> The condition is, <hi>a broken and a contrite heart</hi> for ſin; and if thy <hi>heart</hi> be thus, be ſure <hi>God will not deſpiſe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prov. 28.13. <hi>Whoſoever confeſſeth, and forſaketh his ſins, ſhall have mercy.</hi> The condition is, to <hi>confeſs and forſake ſin:</hi> and this if thou doſt, as ſure as God is God, thou <hi>ſhalt have mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iſa. 57.17. <hi>I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi> The condition is, to be of <hi>a contrite and humble ſpirit;</hi> and if thou art thus, God is true who hath ſaid it, <hi>he dwels in thee, to revive thy ſpirit, and to revive thy heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iſa. 61.1. <hi>The Lord hath anointed me to preach good tidings unto the meek, he hath ſent me to binde up the broken hearted.</hi> The condition is, to be <hi>meek and broken hearted;</hi> and if this be thy caſe, then <hi>good tidings</hi> belong to thee, and Chriſt is ſent <hi>to binde up thy broken heart</hi> in the bundle of peace.</p>
                  <p>Jerem. 31.19, 20. <hi>Surely, after that I was turned, I repented</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:30627:40"/>(ſaith <hi>Ephraim) and after that I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my thigh, I was aſhamed; yea, even confounded, becauſe I did bear the reproach of my youth—Therefore</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>my bowels are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi> The condition is to <hi>repent,</hi> to be <hi>aſhamed, confounded for ſin,</hi> and if thy caſe be like <hi>Ephraims,</hi> God is the ſame to thee, <hi>his bowels yearn for thee, he will ſurely have mercy on thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Matth. 5.6. <hi>Bleſſed are they which hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs.</hi> The condition is, to <hi>hunger and thirſt after the righteouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt; and this if thou doſt, then art thou <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> from the mouth of our Savior.</p>
                  <p>Matth. 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labor, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> The condition is to <hi>labor, and be heavy laden</hi> with ſin; and if thou art thus, Gods Word is ſure, thou ſhalt have <hi>reſt</hi> ſpiritual and eternal.</p>
                  <p>Revel. 21.6. <hi>I will give unto him that is athirſt, of the water of life freely.</hi> The condition is to thirſt after the heavenly ſtreams of Gods favor, and Chriſts ſoveraign blood; and this if thou doſt, then haſt thou part <hi>in the fountain of the water of life, that proceeds out of the throne of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Revel. 22.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and of the Lamb,</hi> Revel. 22.1.</p>
                  <p>All theſe are ſo full of comfort, that if thou but cruſh them with the hand of faith, they cannot but yield ſome juyce of ſweetneſs to thy afflicted ſoul.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 7. <hi>The means to apply the ſaid promiſes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Said before, it was enough for me to prepare the medicine, it is thou muſt apply it; yet if thou feeleſt a backwardneſs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thy part, I ſhall tell thee of ſome <hi>means</hi> to incite thee, and help thee onward to the performance of this duty.</p>
                  <p>Take then the promiſes, and carry them (as thou didſt the Catalogue of thy ſins) into the preſence of the Lord; and, faln down on thy knees, beſeech God for thy Saviors ſake to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine heart to believe thoſe <hi>promiſes.</hi> If thou haſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe, <hi>pray again and again,</hi> yea reſolve never to make prayer, but to uſe this petition, <hi>that the Lord would pleaſe to let thee have ſome feeling of the life of thoſe promiſes;</hi> Some ſoul may object, I have no heart or ſpirit to pray, yet uſe thy indeavor, and in thy
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30627:40"/>indeavors God may come in; and whenſoever thou feeleſt any of them to be <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>life</hi> to thee, whenſoever thou feeleſt (by a certain taſte) <hi>the joys of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> to fall upon thee, O happy man that ever thou waſt born! then art thou (to thy own knowledge) <hi>new born</hi> indeed: then haſt thou (without doubt) done this moſt glorious exerciſe of paſſing thorow <hi>the new birth,</hi> and then haſt thou cauſe (as thou canſt not chooſe) to ſing and praiſe God day and night, world without end:
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.4.</note> So true is that of Chriſt, <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 8. <hi>The Concluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEre is an end, and to you to whom I have dedicated this work, my concluſion is this: The year hath now run his round ſince I firſt came amongſt you, and how the Lord hath wrought by me you your ſelves know beſt: for my part, if I did but know one poor ſoul amongſt you truly converted by ſuch a weak unworthy inſtrument, I would ever think my ſelf moſt happy in that ſoul, and richly payed for my pains. I know it, neither <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Apollo</hi> can do this, except God give the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: howſoever, I muſt tell you, with <hi>Paul,</hi> my deſires have been this way, I have ſince my coming <hi>travelled of you, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled again, that Chriſt might be formed in you.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> And what's the iſſue? once could the Lord ſay, <hi>Shall I bring to the birth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.9.</note> 
                     <hi>and not cauſe to bring forth?</hi> and (to joyn iſſue with you) have I tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled of you in birth, and not one of you brought forth? the Lord forbid. I confeſs (beloved) I have received from you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kindeneſſes of love; now, for the Lords ſake do me this one kindeneſs more; give me at leaſt one ſoul among you, that I may give it unto God: O what a kindeneſs would you then do me! not all the wealth in your Town, nor all the increaſe of your ſtate, nor all you have, or ever ſhall have, would do me ſo much good in the day of my Lord Jeſus, as this one boon I ask: then could I ſay, <hi>Lord, I have not loſt the fruits of my labor in this Town, ſee here the ſoul now ſhining in glory which I converted by thy power; ſee here the ſoul of ſuch a one, and ſuch a one which through thy grace, and my miniſtery were converted unto thee.</hi> If this were thus, why then (beloved) you would bleſs me for ever,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30627:41"/>and I ſhould bleſs you for ever, and we ſhould all bleſs God for ever, for this ſo gracious and ſo bleſſed a work. <hi>Now the Lord of his goodneſs give you a ſight of your ſins, and a true ſorrow for ſin, and if not afore now, yet now, this day, the Lord this day ſet his print and ſeal upon you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The time draws on, and I have but a minute, a little time to ſpeak to you; for a farewel then, let theſe laſt words take a deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er impreſſion in your hearts: if you would do all I would have you do, I could wiſh no more, but that to this <hi>humiliation or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> you would adde <hi>charity or love:</hi> the firſt you owe to <hi>God,</hi> and the ſecond to your <hi>neighbor:</hi> by the firſt you might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new creatures, by the ſecond true Chriſtians, like them in the Churches infancy, <hi>of one minde, one heart, and one ſoul;</hi> ſure it is not poſſible that we ſhould have <hi>forgiveneſs of ſins,</hi> but that we muſt be of the <hi>communion of Saints.</hi> A thouſand pities it is to hear of the many factions in our Church, and Kingdoms, and Towns, and Families, <hi>O pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, they ſhall proſper that love it;</hi> and let us pray (as need we have too) for our own peace one with another: You cannot come to a Communion, but you hear this leſſon in the invitation, <hi>You that do truly and earneſtly repent you of your ſins, and be in love and charity with your neighbors, &amp;c.</hi> Here's both <hi>repentance to God,</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> (nay more then charity, as we uſe the word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly) even <hi>love of your neighbors.</hi> For my part I wiſh that my very heart-blood could cement <hi>the diviſions of Reuben</hi> (for which are <hi>great thoughts of heart</hi>) in this Town,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.15.</note> in this Church, in theſe Kingdoms.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11.</note> I will ſay no more, but conclude with thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Finally brethren, fare ye well, be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one minde, live in peace, and the God of love and peace be with you for ever and ever.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
